<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The illustrious history of women, or, A compendium of the many virtues that adorn the fair sex represented not only in lively and pathetical discourses grounded upon reason, but in sundry rare examples of virtuous love, piety, prudence, modesty, chastity, patience, hnmility [sic], temperance, conduct, constancy, and firmness of mind ... : with the prophesies and predictions of the Sybils ... : the whole work enrich'd and intermix'd with curious poetry and delicate fancie sutable to so charming a subject.</title>
            <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09398729</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09398729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1315:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The illustrious history of women, or, A compendium of the many virtues that adorn the fair sex represented not only in lively and pathetical discourses grounded upon reason, but in sundry rare examples of virtuous love, piety, prudence, modesty, chastity, patience, hnmility [sic], temperance, conduct, constancy, and firmness of mind ... : with the prophesies and predictions of the Sybils ... : the whole work enrich'd and intermix'd with curious poetry and delicate fancie sutable to so charming a subject.</title>
                  <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 158 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: John Shirley.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>emblem of female virtue</figDesc>
                  <q>My reward is above</q>
                  <q>Crescit ſub pondere virtus.</q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Behold Bright <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtues Glorious Emblem plac't</l>
                     <l>Beneath a Crown with beaming Stars Enchas't.</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue like Palms dos under preſsure riſe,</l>
                     <l>And Phoenix like true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue never dies.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>London printed for Iohn Harris at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harrow in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poultrey.</p>
            <byline>I. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:1"/>
            <p>The <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> HISTORY OF WOMEN, OR, A COMPENDIUM of the many Virtues that Adorn the <hi>Fair Sex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Repreſented not only in Lively and Pathetical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes grounded upon Reaſon, but in Sundry rare <hi>Examples</hi> of <hi>Virtuous Love, Piety, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Modeſty, Chaſtity, Patience, Humility, Temperance, Conduct, Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Firmneſs</hi> of <hi>Mind;</hi> with what elſe in the like Nature is neceſſary for the Accompliſhment of the moſt <hi>Celebrated Beauties.</hi> With other Examples of <hi>Women, Skill'd</hi> in the moſt <hi>Curious Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which are Added, the Examples of Warlike Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, their Noble Exploits and Victories: With the Propheſies and Predictions of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> in relation to the Incarnation, continuance upon Earth, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcention of our Bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour:</hi> And as an Apendix, the Character of a Virtuous Woman in all her Capacities.</p>
            <p>The whole Work enrich'd and intermix'd with Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Poetry and Delicate Fancie, ſutable to ſo Charming a Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> againſt the Church in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound One Shilling.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:2"/>
            <p>This may be Printed</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 21 1685.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. L. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>TO ſome it may ſeem ſtrange, that in ſo ſmall a Bark, I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured into an Ocean rarely Navigated; made an Eſſay on what has been ſeldome undertaken, and never Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in it's proper Luſture. The Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Excellencies of the ſofter Sex; a Subject, worthy a more reſined Pen; but ſince the Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſlings of <hi>Appollo,</hi> the <hi>Wits</hi> of the <hi>Age,</hi> have for the moſt part not only declined it, but rather ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died to Eclips the brighteſt Candor of Female perfection, than give it a valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proportion of the praiſe it has merited. I thought it not amiſs to remove the Veile that obſcured it from the Eyes of the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb facs="tcp:42968:3"/>anter part of the Maſculine World, and let them ſee how they have been impoſed upon by the haters and contemners of the Beatious Sex, and conſequently induced to harbour a mean Eſteem of Female vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or the perfections of Women-kind, who in Piety, Conſtancy, Entireſt Love, Amazing Beauty, Arts and Arms, have in all Ages been the boaſt of Nations, and Exemplary, even to a Miracle wadeing with undaunted reſolves through the greateſt of difficulties and dangers, to ſuch Eminence as has rendered them accompliſhed, and ſtilled the hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Snakes of Envy, whilſt thoſe that ſought to croſs their Noble actions, and Clip the Wings of flying Fame, have been obliged to own themſelves o'recome, and tune the ſtrings that were Diſcordant to their praiſes; with which renowned ſtories and examples of Female Worthies, drawn from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique Hiſtories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly filled the following Pages; a Work that may prove grateful, unleſs the Age proves otherwiſe; however, I dare not doubt the approbation of thoſe for whoſe ſakes it was compiled, to whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:42968:3"/>virtues it ows it's Birth, and of ſuch it is, I chiefly wiſh it may find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; which if it does, I have my end, and ſhall remain as heretofore, the admirer of Female virtue. <hi>And. Ladies,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Devoted Servant, JOHN SHIRLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:4"/>
            <head>To the LADIES the Authors APOLOGY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LADIES,</hi> beneath your Virtues Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,</l>
               <l>This little Book wou'd ſhelter from the rage</l>
               <l>Of Carping <hi>Zoliſts,</hi> who ſeldome ſpare</l>
               <l>The <hi>Candor</hi> of the Chaſt, the Wiſe and Fair,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Boreas blaſts,</hi> or like a <hi>Lapland ſtorm:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By <hi>Mild degrees</hi> compel'd is to reform:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Task</hi> was bold, but <hi>Love</hi> and your ſweet <hi>Charms,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made me forget the <hi>Girds</hi> of <hi>Envies Arms,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To your <hi>Fair Sex,</hi> this Book's a Votarie,</l>
               <l>What pitty is it then to let it dye,</l>
               <l>Or Languiſh long? which it alas muſt do,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs 'tis kindly Entertain'd by you:</l>
               <l>Come take it in your Hands, give it a Smile,</l>
               <l>And make it live, though but a little while;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:4"/>
               <l>I'm ſhure to you'ts no Foe, for ſee it wears</l>
               <l>Your Virtues Badge enchac'd with thoſe bright Stars,</l>
               <l>That in the <hi>Female Firmament</hi> do ſhine,</l>
               <l>There rendering you ſo Lovely and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ladies,</hi> once more Protection it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks,</l>
               <l>If not for it's, yet for your omn dear ſakes</l>
               <l>Give ſhelter to it, e're the ſtorm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:5"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>WHEN the Wiſe Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator had furniſhed the Glorious Univerſe in every part with wonderous Varietie, he formed Man, and brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it as into a ſtately Pallace, ſtored with what might pleaſe each Sence, and render him Delight a Thouſand wayes; which great Munificence might have over-charged the largeſt Thought, and put a Limit to the vaſtneſs of deſire; yet the Divine goodneſs thought not this ſufficient for his Darling Favorit, in favour of whom the viſible World was made, &amp; decked in all it's glitering Glories, but opening wider yet his giving Hand; to make his Happineſs the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, he Added a Bleſſing worthier than the reſt, formed of Elements, rarefied by cordial Life and ſoft Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture, giving it at once a Shape
<pb facs="tcp:42968:5"/>and Soul Angelical; the laſt Created, but admired beyond the firſt: A Work, that put a period to the great Work-maſters undertaking, as made to Crown the reſt of the Creation; and that it might be the more Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, gave it a name, ſignifying life, and bowed the lofty Soul of Man to cheriſh and admire it, to place in it next Heaven his chief felicity, by centring in this lovely Creature Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, adding attractive charms and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning graces, ſuch as might captivate the ſtuborneſt heart, and melt the rockie Orbe of ſtrict reſervedneſs, eaſe the labouring of the mind, and ſmooth the rumpled waves of a diſordered paſſion, which made the Enemy of Man-kind ſwell with Envy, and contract a deadly hatred, nouriſhed with a mortal Bane to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in any one creature an adornment of ſo many Excellencies, ſuch an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Coeleſtial Innocence clad in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable Robes of native Beauty, and as it were regreting, that the Favours of the higheſt were ſo largly diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to any Creature of a lower rank
<pb facs="tcp:42968:6"/>than Angels, and that corporeal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhould nearly vie in excellency with incorporial; he layed the guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bait of Aſpiring greatneſs in her way, and with a ſubtill Guile under diſguiſe, prevailed to be believed, and by being credited to affront his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and heap up a vengeance ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, in ſeducing her on whom the Image of the Deitie was livelyly por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, nor was the fraud impoſed as ſome have fancy'd without regret; even Helliſh malice being touch'd with Remorſe, to injure ſuch a lovely frame of Innocence: And thus ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine him at the firſt view of our Grand Parents, to have pondered with himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lwhat do my Eyes with grief behold,</l>
               <l>Earth Born Creatures of a different mould,</l>
               <l>Advanc'd into the happy Realms of Light?</l>
               <l>Not Spirits, yet near to Heavenly Spirits Bright;</l>
               <l>Whom my great Thoughts with wonder do perſue,</l>
               <l>And in them a Divine reſemblance view:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:6"/>
               <l>And cou'd a Love in my hot Breaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</l>
               <l>Of ought, but Miſchief's dire and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bain,</l>
               <l>AConqueſt here perhaps I wou'd not gain.</l>
               <l>Ah lovely Pair! you little think how nigh</l>
               <l>Sad ambuſhments of certain Death do lye,</l>
               <l>When all the Bland delights that Charm you now,</l>
               <l>Will leave you over-caſt with Clouds of woe,</l>
               <l>A Foe is Enter'd your great ſeat of Bliſs,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſelf unpittied pitty muſt Expreſs,</l>
               <l>For you who wrong'd me not, did not a Rage</l>
               <l>'Gainſt him who plac'd you here, my ſpleen ingage;</l>
               <l>A hope of Conqueſt do's compell me now</l>
               <l>To doe what elſe, though dam'd I wou'd not doe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to wave Fancy in ſo profound a miſtery, certain it is, that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy yielding of the faireſt of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the ſubtill Alurements of the fallen Angel (whoſe ſtrength and wiſdome, though much debaſed, is not to be coped with by mortal Might, nor his powerful Temptations, to be over-come without the immediate
<pb facs="tcp:42968:7"/>Divine aſſiſtance) became a means of the Almighties further expreſſing his boundleſs Love to Man-kind, in that great miſtery of Godlineſs, the Incarnation of our Bleſſed Saviour; a Miſtery ſo, ſtupendious and amazing, that all the Hoſt of Heaven, all the bleſſed Hierarchies of <hi>Seraphims</hi> &amp; <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims,</hi> Arch Angels and Angels con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template and admire it, ſo that not without reaſon was the firſt Created Woman called <hi>Eve;</hi> a Name ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying life, ſince from her decended that Glorious Virgin, from whoſe ſpotleſs Womb proceeded the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life and immortality, who wonderfully repaired our firſt defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, by condecending to take our Nature upon him, and revenged our cauſe in breaking the Serpents head, reſtoring us to an undoubted poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of obtaining a more glorious Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe than that from whence our firſt Parents fell.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Womans bleſt Seed to life prepar'd the way,</l>
                  <l>The glorious Path that leads to endleſs day,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42968:7"/>
                  <l>To dazling Manſions, to a place of Bliſs,</l>
                  <l>That Eye ne'r ſaw, nor Tongue cou'd e're expreſs:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then why ſhould man her praiſes due decline,</l>
                  <l>Who is a Sphere wherein all Virtues ſhine;</l>
                  <l>Once the Receſs of him, that's all Divine.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Nor does woman yet deſiſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an Aire of Paradiſe, (the place wherein ſhe was formed) in her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and ſeemly Behaviour, Innocence, Piety, and extradinary Love of ſacred things, as in ſundry Examples are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted; nor does the tranſcendent Beautie exiſtent in many, ſignifie leſs, then that woman is the moſt refined of all Creatures, who deſervedly pay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her as the Queen of all ſublunary things, and perfection of the Univerſe: that perfection being properly termed the Divine Light ſhining on created Eſſence, and beaming thence its luſter by reflex to captivate the Heart, to command a profound Awe and Reverence, as if the perfections ſcattered in all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:42968:8"/>were collected in her, who is a draught of the Creation in mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature: for this cauſe the Lyon nobly bold ſtands in Awe of her; the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn for love of her becomes a wilful captive; nor has the unwieldie Elephant been leſs enamoured with the charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sex: nay, Spirits infernal have been paſſionate, as appears by the oft Eſpouſed Maid, who at laſt was free'd from her <hi>Daemonick</hi> lover <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> and became the Lot of <hi>Tobits</hi> Son. <hi>Abigals</hi> Beauty and Humility pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented <hi>Davids</hi> ſhedding Blood. Queen <hi>Heſter</hi>'s Piety and matchleſs Beauty wrought deliverance to her People, and turned the bloody decree upon the Man and his Houſe that had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted and procured it. <hi>Judiths</hi> Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty charmed the Pagan General, into that ſecurity that wrought his ruin, and the great delivery of her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from the rage of the oppreſſing Sword, reſtoring peace to <hi>Jacobs</hi> Heritage; and after <hi>Jobs</hi> reiterated Tribulations (miſeries that Mortal man could never have undergone, if not ſupported by a hand Divine)
<pb facs="tcp:42968:8"/>the greateſt Earthly recompence for his unparalel'd patience, was that God bleſſed him with Daughters exceeding all other Women in Beauty, which makes <hi>Solomon</hi> ſet a value on them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the price of Rubies, and afirm, <hi>He that findeth a good Wife, findeth a good thing,</hi> &amp;c. And the Author of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> affirmeth that Husband bleſſed, that is Husband of a good Wife; So great has been the eſteem of Female Virtue amongſt the wiſeſt of men in all Ages, Holy writ ſtiling the Woman a Crown, the glory of the Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore ſhe being the compleatment, felicity and glory of Man, it is highly reaſonable ſhe ſhould be loved and eſteemed as ſhe truly deſerves: nay, ſuch was the eſteem of this Sex, that thoſe who gave Names to the three principal parts of the World, as <hi>Aſia, Europe</hi> and <hi>Africa</hi> ſeem to have derived them from the names of women, thereby affording them a laſting memory, not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of end till time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>Should we take a particular ſurvey of the many Virtues of this Sex, what
<pb facs="tcp:42968:9"/>Volume can contain them in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per luſter, or ſet them forth at large? what Rhetorick can Paint them to the life, and not be found therein deficient.</p>
            <p>If Chaſtity we prize, it was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man firſt vowed Virginity to her Maker. If Prophecy, the <hi>Sybils</hi> were ſtrangely inſpired, but more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>Mirriam</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. If conſtancy and ſteadfaſt Love, <hi>Ruth</hi> is a pattern to a Miracle: If a firm grounded Faith, the Widdow of <hi>Sarepta</hi> may juſtly take place, who believed the Prophet in a thing to Humane Senſe impoſſible: If in a ſtrong Belief, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Wife of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> and the Bleſſed Virgin. If con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in a Righteous cauſe, and the contempt of Death, rather than diſobey the God that made us and the World, be a Heroick virtue, behold the Woman who encouraged her ſeven Sons to dye by the moſt exquiſit Tortures, and after ward with joy and patience ſubmitted to the like her ſelf: If for thoſe we have eſteem, whoſe ſacred Charity extends to Souls, let
<pb facs="tcp:42968:9"/>us conſider the <hi>Lumbards,</hi> next to that Saving Grace, that put in with her pious and unwearied endeavors, chiefly owe their converſion to the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> to <hi>Theodilina</hi> Daughter to a King of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> the like do the <hi>Hungarians</hi> to <hi>Greiſil</hi> Siſter to the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt; and the ſame acknowledgment the <hi>Franks</hi> muſt make to <hi>Clotildis</hi> Daughter to a King of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy.</hi> Nor was the Virtuous <hi>Helena</hi> Daughter to King <hi>Colus,</hi> and Wife to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> careleſs not only to protect and ſuccour the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but as far as in her lay, to cauſe that <hi>growing Religion</hi> to take deep Root, in all or moſt of the Provinces of the Empire. In learning deep Sciences and Miſteries of the profoundeſt degree, if attainable by Humane Capacity, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have been found expert. Nay in ſuch rare Inventions as perhaps had yet remained in the dark Embrio of obſcurity, had not Female Wiſdome ſnatched them thence and nurſed them to maturity. The <hi>Gracchi's</hi> Tongues by the induſtry of their Mother <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia,</hi> were made fit Inſtruments of
<pb facs="tcp:42968:10"/>Eloquence, not only to command the Liſtening Ears of <hi>Plebeans,</hi> but thoſe of Aged <hi>Senators,</hi> through which Organs they ſtole the hearts of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering <hi>Rome,</hi> and bowed them to their intreſt. Nor was <hi>Iſtrinia</hi> Queen of <hi>Scythia</hi> leſs Induſtrious in Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Son in that degree of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he Eclipſed the Fame of his great Anceſtors: nor in Phyſick, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Divine Miſteries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have they leſs Excell'd, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear when I come to more particular Examples; and if from Schools we paſs to Courts and Camps, there we ſhallfind the Trump of Fame more loud. <hi>Ophis</hi> for her noble Actions was Reverenced by the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> as a Deitie. <hi>Debora Plotinathe,</hi> Wife of <hi>Trajan. Semirames,</hi> and <hi>Candaces,</hi> were no leſs Famous for Prudence and Conduct, than for Power and Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence: <hi>Thomiris</hi> Queen of the <hi>Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getae,</hi> Subdued the mighty <hi>Cyrus</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the <hi>Meeds</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and having taken him in Battle, cauſed his Head to be ſtricken off, in revenge of haveing ſlain her Son, and caſt it
<pb facs="tcp:42968:10"/>into a Cauldron of Blood, ſaying <hi>that ſince he had thirſted ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Blood, and ſhed it cauſlesſly, be ſhould not want his fill.</hi> The brave <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themeſia</hi> Encountering the Navy of the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> who were on their way to deſtroy her Countrey, Overthrew them in a dreadful Sea fight, and proſecuting her Victory, ſeized upon the Iſle of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> erecting a Trophy in Memory thereof in their Capital City; and yet theſe are but trifles to what has been performed by Noble <hi>Viragoes</hi> whoſe Courage and Conduct has been manifeſted to Admiration; as for Inſtance, the Renowned <hi>Joan</hi> of <hi>Arch</hi> when <hi>France</hi> had ſtooped to <hi>Engliſh Valour,</hi> and all its courage drooped to a degree even of diſpaire, this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Maid by her courage and conduct put ſuch Spirit and Life into the Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearted <hi>French,</hi> that fatal to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſoon after they ſtripped them out of almoſt all the Towns they held in that floriſhing Kingdom. Nor can the World continue without this Sex, were not theſe Virtues found in them, but ſoon would droop in to
<pb facs="tcp:42968:11"/>a ſolitary Deſart; of this, <hi>Rome's</hi> Founders were not Ignorant, when at the hazzard of a doubtful War, they ſeized on the <hi>Sabean</hi> Maids who came to view their Sports, nor were they though Raviſhed at ſuch a rate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary doubtleſs to their Inclinations, when they found themſelves united in Conjugal bands, regardleſs of their Raviſhers, but out of good Nature forgetting the injury: Although their Fathers intending a reſcue, and had taken the <hi>Capitol,</hi> maintaining a bloody Fight, even in <hi>Romes</hi> Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, they with disſheveld hair and crys, ruſhed between the dreadful fronts of War, expoſing themſelves to a Thouſand dangers; nor would retire till they had put an end to that diſaſtrous conflict between their Husbands, and their Fathers, which ſo far moved the hearts of the Latter to relent, that without more adoe Concord and firm Peace enſued. Thoſe Arms that Erſt were bathed in each others Blood, with all reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal Love embrace and mortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is dſlodged from eithers breaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:42968:11"/>which noble Act of theſe Heroick and adventrous Females, made <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Romes</hi> Founder, cauſe their names to be Enroled. Enacting by a Joynt conſent, that Women ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from all Servile Employments, and that there ſhould be no ſuch thing as Property between Husband and Wife, but that all things ſhould be common.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Brutus</hi> heading the <hi>Romans,</hi> upon the Raviſhment of <hi>Luc retia,</hi> had expelled <hi>Tarquin</hi> and his Race, the <hi>Volſci</hi> takeing the opportunity of ſuch a rupture. Advanced with an Army towards <hi>Rome</hi> which for a time filled the City with Fear and amazement, that had not the Noble Matrons by their Conrage and Conduct, Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as it were the hearts of the drooping Souldiers, that afterward Miſtreſs of the World, had become a prey to the Enemy; whoſe retreat when within five miles of the Walls, was ſolely attributed to the courage of a Female Worthy. Whereupon a famous Temple was dedicated to Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Fortune, and many notable Marks
<pb facs="tcp:42968:12"/>conferred upon them by the Senate: as takeing the upper hand of the Men, wearing of Purple, Gold, Fringe, Jewels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by the Laws of lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Emperors, Weomen were enabled to Succeed in the right of Inheritance. And that Sacred right of Ecomiaſtick Orations at their Funerals: and it was Provided in an Act Prohibiting the Sumpteouſneſs of Apparrel, that the Women ſhould be exempted and left at their Liberty.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Cammillius</hi> had made a Vow to <hi>Appollo</hi> and all the <hi>Roman</hi> Treaſures could not furniſh him with the Sum, the generous Matrons of <hi>Rome</hi> for the Honour of their Countrey, brought in their Rings, Bracelets, and other Ornaments of Gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> Warring with <hi>Aſtiages,</hi> his Grandfather being overthrown in a great Battle, had that Battle reſtored him by a reinforcement of <hi>Perſian</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, nor is it unuſuall for thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Dames to go with their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to the Wars, and often ſighting coragiouſly by their ſides, for which noble Act, <hi>Cyrus</hi> as a token of his
<pb facs="tcp:42968:12"/>Gratitude left it is a Law, that when any King of <hi>Perſia</hi> entered the Regal City they ſhould beſtow on each Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man a Medall as a remembrance of that Noble Action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Renowned Emperour finding the pregnant Wit and gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit of his Empreſs to excell, conſulted her in the compilement of thoſe excellent Inſtitutes, which all ſucceeding Generations have held in admiration, and many Kingdoms ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their Mold from them; nor did the famous Law-giver <hi>Licurgus,</hi> leſs eſteem the Wiſdome of the Female Sex, ordering them an equal ſhare in all honeſt Paſtimes and Recreations. The Divine <hi>Plato</hi> was no leſs ſedulous in promoting the eſteem of Women, as having ſtudied their Worth and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency; nor were our Countrey wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men leſs Valiant in withſtanding the Comqueſt of the <hi>Romans,</hi> nor leſs Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Bleeding Land in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a means to Extirpate or Expell the <hi>Danes,</hi> which occaſioned this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:13"/>
            <q>
               <l>When <hi>England</hi> bleeding lay to gaſp her laſt:</l>
               <l>When powerful Foes had graſp'd her Scepter faſt:</l>
               <l>When Men ſtood mute with Grief and Fear ſtruck Dumb,</l>
               <l>The Bloody Foe by Women was o're<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:</l>
               <l>Who each in Darkneſs with a Fata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Blade,</l>
               <l>An Expiation to loſt Honour made;</l>
               <l>So raſhly Raviſh'd &amp; diſpiſing Charms</l>
               <l>Earch gave her Raviſher a Death lock'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in her Arms;</l>
               <l>And by thoſe ſtrokes, which ſome wou'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cruel call,</l>
               <l>They ſav'd their Countrey ready then to fall.</l>
               <l>And let the World perceive it was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they</l>
               <l>Who gave their honour, but 'twas forc'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> away:</l>
               <l>So fall each Raviſher, who dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane</l>
               <l>This noble Sex, with ſuch a Lawleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtaine.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:13"/>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, who that proceeded from a Woman, can but admire and eſteem the Sex, whoſe tender care to their off-ſpring is ſuch, that no wakeful vigilance, no care, pain or danger is thought too much; may, even Death it ſelf has not in ſuch a caſe been ſhunned, but rather court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it's dreadful ſhape, in ventering on Swords, and ruſhing through the flames to ſave their Darlings from untimely Fate, or periſh with them: nor for their Husbands have their care been leſs, as many examples of ſuch boundleſs Love and dear Affection can teſtifie; wherefore ſeeing Man owes half his Life to Woman, what leſs returns for ſuch a Care and tender Affection can he make then all his Love that Heaven permits him to place upon Earthly things? And thoſe that do otherwiſe where it is lawfull degenerate from the Nobleneſs of the firſt created Rational, and therein diſobey their Maker, whoſe Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Command it is. And with the entireſt Integrity having carried my diſcourſe on this worthy Subject
<pb facs="tcp:42968:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:15"/>thus far in General. I ſhall now proceed to what is more Particular and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empler in the Praiſe of Women-kind, though as I have ſaid, all their Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in this nature to deſcribe, will prove too large a Theam.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For who but one with Eagles Eyes can Gaze,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Sun in it's Meridian Blaze.</l>
               <l>Or without <hi>Solomons</hi> large Heart can know,</l>
               <l>All from the <hi>Ceder</hi> to the <hi>Shrub</hi> below.</l>
               <l>Or name each fair Enamel, that does ſpread,</l>
               <l>Earth's lovely boſom, when the winters fled.</l>
               <l>What Marriner can count the waves that riſe?</l>
               <l>Or Artiſt tell the wanderers of the Skies,</l>
               <l>Who is the Man can count the flying Clouds,</l>
               <l>Or tell she Fry the ſwelling Ocian Shrowds?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:15"/>
               <l>Who in Arithmatick a Number can,</l>
               <l>Find for the Moments paſt ſince time began?</l>
               <l>Or in an age count out by ſwift De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</l>
               <l>The countleſs Sands forſaken by the Seas?</l>
               <l>Hard tasks theſe are for mortal Man to do.</l>
               <l>Yet full as eaſy as at once to view.</l>
               <l>Each glorious Cabinet where Virtue reſts.</l>
               <l>To look into each worthy Female Breaſt.</l>
               <l>To count the Sacred Treaſure horded there.</l>
               <l>And tell the World of each peculiar ſhare.</l>
               <l>Layd up to Purchaſe an Imortal Name.</l>
               <l>Recorded in the deathleſs Book of Fame.</l>
               <l>To Purchaſe Robes of White to paſs the Gate.</l>
               <l>Where for them Virtues, true Reward does wait.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:42968:16"/>
               <l>Though it on Earth ſhould hiſs it's great deſert.</l>
               <l>Yet there it will be ſure to find it's part.</l>
               <l>For in that Region is it's proper Seat,</l>
               <l>There Virtue and not Riches makes us great.</l>
               <l>Crowns us with Life, and an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal State.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42968:16"/>
            <head>The <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> HISTORY OF WOMEN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="examples">
               <div n="chaste love" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Chaſt-Love.</head>
                  <p>TO come nearer to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for the beſter eaſe and underſtanding of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I ſhall proceed in a Regular way on Method, placing together as near as is convenient, the memorable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of one kind, as I find them in divers Hiſtories highly approved by the Learned of the preſent and paſt Ages. And in this Caſe <hi>Chaſt-Love</hi> being the Center and Baſis of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Virtues, I ſhall begin with that perfection of Woman-kind.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42968:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eurialus</hi> Count of <hi>Auguſta</hi> being at <hi>Sienna</hi> with the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmond Lucretia</hi> a Beautiful Virgin, called by ſome the ſecond <hi>Venus,</hi> upon his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Addreſs conceived ſuch Entire Affection for him, that at his neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted leaving her to attend his Lord, the Emperour to <hi>Rome,</hi> his Abſence wrought ſo much upon her tender Spirits, that having ſtrugled a while with the flame of a conſtant paſſion; ſhe no longer able to indure the Abſence of one on whom ſhe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed her Heart, yielded up her ſelf into the Icey Aims of Death, calling on her Lover, and with dying mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs, beg'd a Bleſſing might ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main upon him: of which ſad mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune <hi>Eurialus</hi> having notice, took it ſo much to heart, that in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he never was obſerved to Laugh or Smile. <hi>Marcel. Donat. Hiſt. Med. Mirab.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theodora</hi> a Chriſtian Virgin, for that Sacred Profeſſion being Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Stews,</hi> where her chaſtity was to be expoſ'd to the violation of the worſt of Villains: <hi>Dydimus</hi> who En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42968:17"/>loved her; whilſt the <hi>Debauchees</hi> were ſtriving to enter, there preſſed in in a Souldiers habit, a Perſon pretending to have the firſt knowledge of that Beautious Maid, but being Retired, he changed Habit with her, by which means ſhe was enabled to eſcape; but he, upon others preſſing in, being found a man, was halled before the Judg, who had ſhameleſsly Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Theodora</hi> to looſe her Virginity, who immediately Sentanc'd him to Death; of which ſhe having notice, came from her Retirement, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her life a Ranſom for his; but ſuch Tranſcendent-love nothing moved the Inexorable Judge, who inſtead of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the offer, commanded they ſhould both be immediately put to Death; which command being obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their Souls took flight to the bright Manſion of Eternal Love. <hi>Lonicer. Theatri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Story related of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful love of <hi>Piramus</hi> and <hi>Thiſbe</hi> is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable; nor is it held in the general Fabulous, though <hi>Ovid</hi> has glozed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; the ſubſtance being this: The
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42968:18"/>Beautious Pair living as Neighbours in <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bylon,</hi> when grown to maturity, found themſelves ſurpriz'd with a generous flame, love had made a mighty conqueſt o're their hearts; their M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> affections could not be ſo cloſely hid, but Parents of a different mind, in whom Age had quench'd the fire of paſſion, came to know the caſe wherein they ſtood, and cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ly proceeded to divorce their Joys by ſeperation; but mighty love, that like the Victorious <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alm,</hi> laden with ponderous Weights, under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint ancreaſes, found an unſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed way to Whiſper through a Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and by that means to ſet a time for ſlight, when the Moon had thrown her Silver Mantle over the Shadie Night. The place being appointed, <hi>Thiſbe</hi> raviſh'd with eager Joys, to have her Lover in her Arms, firſt made Eſcape; but there, inſtead of <hi>Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats</hi> ſhe found a Lyoneſs beſmeer'd with blood, which made her haſten to a Neighbouring Cave, whilſt in her ſlight ſhe drop'd her Veile, which the Lyoneſs finding, rumpled it with her
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42968:18"/>Bloody Jaws, and went her way; <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> ſoon after coming, and finding the Veile he knew to be hers all ſmeer'd with Blood, and the Footſteps of a wild Beaſt, ſuppoſed her devour'd, and after many doleful lamentations, Exclaiming againſt himſelf, for expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſuch hazard, a thing he prized ſo dear, reſolving not to live without her, he ſell upon his Sword; when <hi>Thiſbe</hi> diſpenſing with her fear, came to the place and found him Breathing out his laſt, having no more Senſe than at her Name to open his dying Eyes and ſee his dear miſtake, which was not long e're cloſing again he was left in the black Miſt of Death; when having expreſſed her ſelf with the diſordered paſſion of a diſtracted lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſcorning a tedious life, when he for whom ſhe liv'd was gone, ſhe bared her Snowey Breaſt, and with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage fell upon the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Sword. <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ids Met,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Leſs Famous than this is not, the admirable love of the Beautious <hi>Hero</hi> to the <hi>Greecian</hi> Youth <hi>Leander,</hi> whoſe memorable loves famed the threatning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42968:19"/>Towers of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abidos,</hi> in the former the Noble Virgin dwelt, and from the latter, parted by the <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpont,</hi> the adventerous Youth often Swam to viſit her, ſhe being his Load-Star to ſtear his Courſe in the darkeſt Night, by placing a light in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Turret; but after often adventring with ſucceſs, Fate croſſing Love, in raiſing a Tempeſt whilſt he was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Ocean, the undiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Waves put a period to his life, and then unkindly, caſt his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Corps upon the ſhoar, where he with ſuch Eagerneſs wiſh'd to come alive; at ſight of which, the Lady being over-come with Grief, leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed headlong from the Tower, and plunging into the Remorſleſs Deep, became partaker of her Lovers Fate.</p>
                  <p>The Beautious Daughter of the Emperour <hi>Charlemain,</hi> falling in love with <hi>Eginardus,</hi> Secretary to that Emperour, nor was the flame he felt leſs violent: he one Night coming in private to her Chamber, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to Snow; which accident, by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42968:19"/>reaſon it was ſomewhat late, did not a little trouble the Lovers, leaſt upon his return, the prints of his Feet ſhould be obſerved the next Morning, which coming from the Ladies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, might create a ſuſpition; to prevent which, love which takes the <hi>Diadem</hi> of Majeſty from Queens, made this lovely Princeſs, do an Act for a Lover, very unbeſeeming and unuſual for the Daughter of ſo great a Potentate, <hi>viz.</hi> She took the <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> upon her Shoulders and carried him all the length of the Court to his Chamber, he not ſetting Foot to the Ground, and there delivering her burthen returned: yet ſo it happen'd, that during this piece of Portrage, the Emperour being late in his Studie, chanc'd to look out and behold it, yet at that time kept ſilence: when the next day, in a great Aſſembly of his Lords, his Daughter and <hi>Eginardus</hi> being preſent, he demanded what Puniſhment he deſerved, who made uſe of a Kings Daughter; as of a Mule, and cauſed himſelf to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on her Shoulders in the middeſt of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42968:20"/>Winter through the Snow; upon this every one gave his opinion, that he was worthy of Death; which ſtarted the Lovers and made them change their colour, expecting ſome dreadful puniſhment; but contrary to their expectation, the Emperour, looking upon his <hi>Secretary</hi> with a ſmooth Countenance, <hi>Eginardus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hadeſt thou loved the Princeſs, my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou oughteſt to have come to her Father, the diſpoſer of her liberty; thou art worthy of Death, yet I give thee two lives; Tale thy ſair Portreſs in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; fear God, and love one another.</hi> The Joy theſe lovers conceived, at ſo unexpected a happineſs, I leave to the Imagination of the Reader. <hi>Caus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Court. Tom.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Princeſs <hi>Xexin</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Muley Moluck,</hi> King of <hi>Fes</hi> and <hi>Moro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o,</hi> upon the Fame of <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal</hi> though an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who came to Invade her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Countrey conceived ſo great a love for him, that when his Army was overthrown on the plains of <hi>Tamiſta</hi> near. <hi>Alcazar</hi> and himſelf ſlain She
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42968:20"/>came e're the day dawn'd accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with one ſlave named <hi>Laura;</hi> to ſeek him amongſt the heaps of the dead, when entring that miſerable Scene of Slaughter She Inquired of ſome wounded men that were yet breathing, where the King Fought, and with many abrupt ſtammerings being informed by thoſe dying wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, She haſted thither reſolving to Sacrifice her Life, and fall upon him, when comming to the heap of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lain She eſpyed one extreamly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling her Lover, for She had ſeen the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> often, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon with great cries She embraced and moved him, but being about to offer violence to her ſelf; She found the ſuppoſed dead Man to breath, and after ſome rubbing and chafeing he came to himſelf. So that binding up his wounds, She and her Slave with the help of a Matriner conveighed him into a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>land in the River <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>azen,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere provided all things for him, verily ſuppoſing him the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> for indeed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had made this Subject (for ſo he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42968:21"/>proved, and not the King of <hi>Portugal</hi>) ſo like his Prince that the <hi>Portugals</hi> themſelves were deceived, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. This Man thus ſnatch'd from death, being continually attended by the Princes, who infinitly doated on him, and uſed him like a vallued Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, began to wonder from whence the cauſe of ſuch mighty Kindneſs ſhould ſpring, when one day after a Sigh She ſaid, <hi>Heaven will not deprive</hi> Portugal <hi>of it's King, but has made your</hi> Xerine <hi>Happy in ſaving her dear</hi> Don Saebaſtians <hi>Life,</hi> by this Speech he found the Princes Error yet thought it not convenient to undeceive her but rather to promote it, and ſo by inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation he came to underſtand who She was, as likewiſe her Love to the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſo far he prvailed upon that Princes; that She thought nothing too dear for him, but uſed her Intereſt with <hi>Muley Boabdelin</hi> a <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Prince and her <hi>Conzen,</hi> to Entertain him in his Pallace at <hi>Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core</hi> till ſuch time as She could furniſh him with a train ſuitable for a King (as She ſuppoſed him to be) to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42968:21"/>return to his own Countrey.</p>
                  <p>This old <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Prince, verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved him to be as his Conzen had reported and Imagining if he got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Portugal</hi> he would not regard the Vows he had made to Marry her; cauſed them to be Married out of hand, ſhe in conſideration thereof promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to become a Chriſtian which She afterwards performed; being a Lady exceeding beautifull as Born of a <hi>Greek</hi> Mother, and conſequently much whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the <hi>Affricans,</hi> and ſoon after provided him an Equipage to go for <hi>Portugal,</hi> to which Crown <hi>Henry</hi> who ſucceded <hi>Saebaſtian</hi> being dead many ſaid claym, but at length it was graſped by the King of Spain, who proved the ſtronger, wherefore he firſt arrived in <hi>Italy,</hi> and was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Dutcheſs of <hi>Parma</hi> who as the former verily believed him to be the true <hi>Saebaſtian;</hi> as likewiſe did ſome Miniſters ſent from the Eſtates of <hi>Portugal</hi> which made him in the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>magine himſelf to be no leſs, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng denied poſſeſſion of that Kingdom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e drew a great power after him, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42968:22"/>being defeated on the Frontiers of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and taken Priſoner, after which being brought to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and Impriſoned as an Impoſter; at what time <hi>Xerine</hi> was come out of <hi>Afric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to aſſiſt him, in the recovery (as She thought of his right) She having by this time had a Son by him, but thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Misfortune did not at all alter th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Love of the Princeſs; who earneſtly laboured for his deliverance: often viſiting him in Priſon where falling ſick and at the point of Death, he declared how he had deceived her, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the King of <hi>Portugal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> yet for all that her Love abated not but She in the beſt wiſe comforted him. <hi>Afflict not your ſelf</hi> (ſaid th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Generous Princeſs) <hi>with too late and unuſeful Repentance I lov'd the Perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of</hi> Don Sebaſtian, <hi>more then the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of his condition; I thought I had me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that Perſon in you. Thoſe Charms which firſt touch'd me, have loſt none of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> priviledg, becauſe they were not place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Monarch, <hi>though I confeſs I ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> never have obſerved them in an Ordinar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Mam, Neither my Spirit nor my Birth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42968:22"/>would have permitted me to conſider whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> had not thought a</hi> Prince, <hi>but my error became dear to me, and is ſo ſtill, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it proves fatal to my peace. The name of Husband is ſo Sacred to a Woman truly Virtuous, that it obli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates any ſhame which accompanyes it: Therefore try to overcome your Ilneſs my dear Prince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (pardon the name) For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ne,</hi> (ſaid She lifting up her Eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Heaven), <hi>might have given it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> She gave you me. Reſcue your ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f it be poſſible, from the arms of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t may be we may find you a happyneſs, more calm and happy than that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enyed you in</hi> Portugal. With this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſs of Female Generoſity the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eit <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> was ſo mov'd that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould no longer ſuffer the Tranſports <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f it, but in the Armes of the Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate <hi>Xerine</hi> expir'd whoſe Soul with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch difficulty ſtaved behind, loving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im even as her Life, who had injur'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er with ſo great a deceit: <hi>Sir, J. B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Rocoles of Impoſtors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Wife of <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xamut,</hi> a Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt Captain of the <hi>Alarbes</hi> had ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reat affection for her Husband, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42968:23"/>whilſt he liv'd She never diſobey'd or diſoblig'd him, and when he dyed, She almoſt drown'd in Tears, cauſed his Funeral Obſequies to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the ſolemneſt manner, with infinite coſt; nor would be Induced to forſake his Tomb: where after Nine days Faſting ſhe dyed, breathing out her laſt Breath by his Side.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>He firſt Deceas'd, She for a few days try'd,</l>
                     <l>To live without him, lik'd it not and dy'ds.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Camer. Oper. Subciſiv.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Emperour <hi>Conrade</hi> the Third, beſieging <hi>Guelphus</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> in the City of <hi>Wenſberg</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> the Women made a requeſt to that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, that they might paſs out with ſo much as they could carry upon their backs, which was granted, he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they would lade themſelves with their Furniture; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, theſe loving Dames preferring the ſafety of their Husbands before all Earthly Riches, took each of them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42968:23"/>their Husbands &amp; carried them as Packs; which Act of Love ſo moved the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that he wept; &amp; not only recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Duke into his favour, but gave all the men their lives, extolling the Womens Tranſcednent Love with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Praiſe. <hi>Lonicer. Theatr.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> afterward <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> whilſt he Warred in the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the City of <hi>Accone,</hi> being ſtab'd with an Impoiſon'd Knife, by one <hi>Auzazim</hi> a <hi>Sarazin,</hi> who had the opportunity of aproaching him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pretence of a Meſſage from one of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Governours, when all hopes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure failed, his Virtuous Wife <hi>Elenor</hi> at the hazzard of her Life, daly ſuck'd the Wounds, till the Venom of the poiſon was extracted, for which amazing Love, when he came to be King, he cauſed her Arms, as Memorials of Conjugal affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to be fixed on divers publick places. <hi>Bakers Cron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sulpitia</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> after the <hi>proſcribing,</hi> of her Husband, by the Influence of the Triumvire, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42968:24"/>his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight to <hi>Pompy</hi>'s Son in <hi>Sicily;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſtrict <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſet upon her, found means to eſcape in diſguiſe, not weighing the danger o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> being proſcribed her ſelf, equal to the Fidelity, to her Husband.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eumonus</hi> burying the dead, fallen in the Battle of <hi>Sabin,</hi> where the <hi>Indians</hi> Warr'd with <hi>Amigonus,</hi> amongſt the ſlain was found the body of <hi>Cereas</hi> an <hi>Indian,</hi> who commanded thoſe Troops<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which man according to the Cuſtom of that Countrey, had at ſundrey times Married two Wives, both which Lov'd him entirely; for, whereas there was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and is yet in ſome places obſerved, that the live Wife ſhall be bunrt with the dead Husband; theſe Women were ſo far from declineing it, that they ſtrove which of them ſhould make her Bed with him in the Flames, as if they had contended for ſome Glorious Prize, the laſt Marry'd of theſe pleaded before the Judges, that were to decide the Controverſie that the former was with Child, and therefore ought to be exempted, to which the other aledg'd, it was fit
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42968:24"/>ſhe ſhould bell before her in Honour, as the elder Marry'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cuſtomary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> things, and after a long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> between them, the Judges being inform'd by the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives, that the Elder Marry'd was with Child, adjudged the Younger ſhould have her deſire, which done the other departed rending her Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, Hair, and Garments, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loud Laments, as if ſome grievous calimity had befaln her. The other overjoy'd at her Victory, in the moſt Magnificient attire, as if ſhe had been going to her Wedding, was led by her friends to the Pile whereon her Husband lay, Singing all the way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there arriv'd, taking off all her Ornaments, ſhe deliver'd them to her Friends and Servants, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance; they conſiſting of a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Rings, with variety of Precious Stones, Chains, and Stars of Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This done ſhe was by her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Placed upon the Pile, by her Husband, which Pile, after the Army had thrice compaſs'd, it was Fir'd, and ſhe without ſo much as a groan,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42968:25"/>finiſh'd her life in the flame, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Invincible Love and Female Courage; and might juſtly, were it not ſome what Eclipſ'd by the name of a Self-violence, ſtand the glory of the Sex. <hi>Didor. Sicul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Such <hi>Phaenixes</hi> the World does rarely yield,</l>
                     <l>No Nation boaſts them but the <hi>Indian</hi> Field.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pondoerus</hi> a <hi>Perſian</hi> Captain, being in Arms againſt <hi>Jacobus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and Son to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſan Caſſants;</hi> his Wife a Beautiful Lady, not exceeding fifteen years, beſought him by all the Ties of love to lay down his Arms and ſubmit; but notwithſtanding he lov'd her entirely, yet would not yield to her requeſt. Then ſhe deſir'd him, and adjur'd him by all that was Sacred, that he would kill her before he gave Battle, that it might not be ſaid ſhe out-liv'd him; but he regarding more his head-ſtrong Ambition than her Tears, whom Grief made lovely, ſounded the Charge, and was ſlain in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42968:25"/>Fight: his Lady was likewiſe taken Priſoner, and by the King beſtowed upon one of his Captains, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating her to receive him as her Husband, with many proffers of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and great preſents. She won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully oppoſed, but perceiving he would have that by force, which by fair means he could not obtain, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired time to conſider the point, and thereupon retiring, ſent him a Note, wherein was written, <hi>That none ſhould ſay the Wife of</hi> Pondoerus <hi>did long ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive him,</hi> and with that ſhe fell upon a Sword and died. <hi>Fulgoſ. l.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Since he was gone, to whom her love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd,</l>
                     <l>She lik'd not life, and wou'd not ſtay behind.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cedrenus</hi> in his Hiſtory tells us, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the ninth, cauſed the <hi>Roman Argyrapalis</hi> to be brought before him, together with his Wife, a Beautious young Lady, threatning him with all the Torments imaginable, if he did not put her away, and in her ſtead
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42968:26"/>take his Daughter; which if he did he promis'd to make him his He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and raiſe him by other promotions in the Empire. The man at this, ſtood confounded with in himſelf, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to Anſwer; when the Lady perceiving what danger he was likely to fall into, if he refuſed to comply with the Emperours demand, <hi>Ah S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (ſaid ſhe to her Husband) <hi>I ſee you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> much hindred in a brave way, if it on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> reſt in your wife, that you be not grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and happy; I freely deprive my ſelf of all yea of your Company, which is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to me than all the Empires of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> World, rather then prejudice your Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, for know I love you better tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> my life.</hi> And ſo ſaying, out of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der compaſſion, to the preſervatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of him ſhe lov'd ſo dear, ſhe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> off her Hair; and enter'd into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, ſpending the reſt of her day in Piety and Divotion. <hi>Cauſ. H. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in treat of paſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Turning the Torrent of her Earth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> love,</l>
                     <l>To a mere laſting Sence of Joys abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42968:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arria,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Cecinna Poetus,</hi> having notice that her Husband was Condemned to dye, yet liberty given him to chooſe his death, ſhe went to him, and exhorted him to Breath his laſt with Conſtancy and Courage, and after having taken a dear farewell, ſhe ſtab'd her ſelf with a Knife ſhe had hid under her Garments, and drawing it out only ſaid, e're ſhe fell dead at his Feet, <hi>The wound I have made</hi> Paetus <hi>ſmarts not, but that only which thou art about to give thy ſelf. Camer. Oper. Subſic.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon this Extravegant effect of paſſionate love, <hi>Martial</hi> made this <hi>Epigram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When <hi>Arria</hi> to her Huſband gave the Knife,</l>
                     <l>Which made the wound whereby ſhe loſt her life,</l>
                     <l>This wound dear <hi>Poetus,</hi> grieves me not, ſaid ſhe,</l>
                     <l>But that which thou muſt give thy ſelf grieves me.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:42968:27"/>
                  <p>In the Reign of <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> the <hi>Gaules</hi> Rebell'd, under the leading of <hi>Julius Sabinus,</hi> But being reduced, their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was ſought for, but having hid himſelf in the Monument of his Grand-Father, to which none but two of his freed men were privy; it was given out that he had poiſoned himſelf, and the better to colour it, he cauſed his Houſe to be ſet on fire, that his Body might be ſuppoſed therein to be burnt; his Wife <hi>Eponiva,</hi> not knowing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, made great Sorrow, inceſſantly Weeping, and refuſing either Food, or to be Comforted; of which, thoſe that were private to his hiding, told their Lord, deſiring him to take pitty on their Lady who was determined to die, and in order thereto, had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from all manner of Food, for the ſpace of three days, by undecei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her, to ſave the Woman that lov'd him ſo well; which was granted, and ſhe brought to the place, where find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him alive, ſhe flew into his Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with all the eager Joys of a tender Wife, and in that doleſome place lived with him nine years, bringing forth Children: But in the end, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42968:27"/>place of their Aboad was diſcover'd, and they brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> where this Virtious Lady ſhewing her Children to <hi>Veſpaſian. Behold, O</hi> Coeſar (ſaith ſhe) <hi>ſuch as I have brought forth, and Nouriſhed in a Monument, that thou mighteſt have more ſupplyants for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> our lives.</hi> But that Emperour baniſhing Compaſſion, commanded them both to be ſlain. The Lady joyfully dying with her Husband, with whom ſhe had been, as it were, Buryed ſo many years. <hi>Lips. Monit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clara Cervenda</hi> was one of the moſt Beautiful Virgins in all <hi>Bruges,</hi> ſhe Married one <hi>Bernard Valdaura,</hi> a Man Aged and wonderfully Infirm, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the foul Diſeaſe he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in his Youth, and in the end growing ſo Ulcerous and ſo Naucious, that the Chyrurgion fled the Scent of him; yet this Tender Lady for the ſpace of Twenty years continually watch'd and tended him, not imagining any thing too dear for him; and when their Money by that large Expence fail'd, ſhe ſold her Jewels and wearing Apparel, Diſrobing, and in a manner
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42968:28"/>ſtarving her ſelf to ſupport him. So ſacred to this virtuous Lady was the name of Husband, and even of ſuch a one as had brought her to Ruine and Miſery; nay, when he was rotted away, that his ſhatter'd Body could no longer retain his fleeting Soul, ſhe made great Lamentation; and when ſome inſtead of comforting of her, told her that God had done much in taking him away, and for that reaſon they came to congratulate her She turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide and would not hear them, but with a mournful Voice, <hi>wiſhed for her Huſband again, and that ſhe would give any thing in the world could ſhe Retrieve him.</hi> Being ſought by many in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, her Anſwer was, <hi>That ſhe could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> meet with any whom ſhe could love, or like ſo well as her deceaſed Huſband.</hi> Camerar Oper Subſic.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So truly loving was this conſtant Dame,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe deſerves a place i'th Book of Fame.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nor is Woman-kind only found ſuch an admirable pattern to Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42968:28"/>but the Sex has prov'd as faithful Woman to Woman, as appears by the following Relation: <hi>Bona</hi> a noble Virgin living in a Nunery, contracted ſo great a Friendſhip with a Beautiful Maid, not exceeding her in years, that they appear'd to thoſe that obſerved their actions, to have but one Soul, their affections were ſo united and met ſo exactly in every thing. But ſo it happened to the unſpeakable grief of <hi>Bona,</hi> that Death, in proceſs of time, with his Icey hand, ſeiz'd upon her dear Companion, the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of her thoughts, and only ſharer of her beſt affections, ſealing her Eyes in Gloomy Night, which cauſed a flood of pious grief to flow from the ſurviving Lady: In the exceſs of which, <hi>ſhe earneſtly beg'd ſhe might not ſtay behind, but that their Bodies might poſſeſs one Grave.</hi> Although this was a raſh wiſh, yet it was anſwered: <hi>For ſhe, e're the other was Buried dyed, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that one Funeral Solemnity ſerv'd them both.</hi> Marul. Lib. 3. C. 3.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42968:29"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity</hi> together dy'd,</l>
                     <l>Raviſh'd by Death, they in one Grave abide.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>How great likewiſe hath the love of Mothers been towards their Children, which for Brevities ſay I ſhall inſtance, but in two Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monica,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Aguſtine,</hi> whilſt her Son in his Youth followed lewd Courſes, ceas'd not to Pray day and night for his Converſion; and doubtleſs her Prayers were heard, which may be gathered by the ſtrangeneſs of his being made ſenſible of the dangerous condition he was in; which occaſioned St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her in this wiſe: <hi>It's impoſſible</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that a Son of ſo many Prayers and Tears can miſcarry.</hi> Clarks. Mir.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>For love to Souls, all other love excells,</l>
                     <l>It muſt be Heaven where ſuch an Angel dwells.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Women of <hi>Carthage,</hi> in the third <hi>Punick</hi> War, when they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Senate</hi> had agree'd to ſend the noble Youths of that City into <hi>Sicily</hi> as a Hoſtage, in conſideration
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42968:29"/>of a peace with the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious was the ſorrow of thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe Sons were ſo to be ſnatc'd from them, that nothing was heard but Cryes, Sighs and ſad Laments; and when they were going to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque,</hi> they followed them in the like manner, huging them in their ſtrict Embraces, with Countenances full of Care and Sadneſs, to hinder their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as loath to take their ſad fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well; but finding they were ſnatch'd from them by the Officers who were to ſee them ſafe delivered and thruſt on Bord, as ſoon as the Ships put off, many of thoſe woeful Mothers leap'd into the Sea after them, and were overwhelm'd by the Relentleſs Waves. <hi>Sebel. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>This ſad Diſaſter occaſioned the following Lines.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When as the two Renown'd Republiques Jar'd,</l>
                     <l>When Mighty <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Carthage</hi> long had War'd.</l>
                     <l>To try by dint of Sword, which Fate deſign'd,</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42968:30"/>
                     <l>Miſtreſs ot'h World, and Ruler of Mankind.</l>
                     <l>Tir'd with the tedious bloodſhed that Imbrew'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> a Peace inſu'd.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Carthage</hi> often breaking 'twas thought fit,</l>
                     <l>They ſhould with ſpeed their noble Touths commit</l>
                     <l>For more ſecurity to <hi>Roman</hi> bands,</l>
                     <l>As Hoſtages, but when to Foraign Lands</l>
                     <l>The Woful Mothers knew their Sons muſt go,</l>
                     <l>What Scenes of ſorrow, did great <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhow?</l>
                     <l>Nothing but Crys, but Sighs, and Groans were heard;</l>
                     <l>But when for their Embarquement they prepar'd</l>
                     <l>The Storm grew loud, each tender Mother run,</l>
                     <l>And in her arms, Infolds her weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Son.</l>
                     <l>Bathing his Cheecks, in tears to add a Store,</l>
                     <l>To thoſe that trick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'d from his Eys before.</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42968:30"/>
                     <l>But finding that the hard Decree was paſt,</l>
                     <l>And that this fare wel ſeem'd to be their laſt.</l>
                     <l>When from their arms their Darling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> dears were forſt,</l>
                     <l>And they from them by ſwelling waves Divorſt.</l>
                     <l>Impatient to out-live ſo great a loſs,</l>
                     <l>Such a heart breaking, ſuch a wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Croſs.</l>
                     <l>They plung'd themſelves into the rowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deep.</l>
                     <l>And vainly ſtrove to reach the flying Ship.</l>
                     <l>In which their Treaſure was but that forbid,</l>
                     <l>By Neptune was, and they In's waves were hid.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="chastity" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Chaſtity.</head>
                  <p>And thus much for extraordinary Paſſion from which I ſhall proceed to Examples of wonderful Chaſtity, the brighteſt Jewel that Adorns the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>As <hi>Bards</hi> of old Enobl'd for their Verſe,</l>
                     <l>Victorious actions did alowd rehearſe,</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:42968:31"/>
                     <l>The conqueſt of great Nations, and the praiſe</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe, whoſe Valour truly claim'd the Bays.</l>
                     <l>So tell we now of Triumphs greater far,</l>
                     <l>Than e're atchived were by'th God of War,</l>
                     <l>Or cou'd be boaſted by that Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</l>
                     <l>A glorious conqueſt over Lawleſs love</l>
                     <l>Triumphs, that all the Chaſter World approve,</l>
                     <l>So in their Spher's, the Bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels move,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvalu'd Chaſtity, Womans chief grace.</l>
                     <l>Next Lawful Paſſion we think fit to place.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And in this kind the Female Sex excell, many of them prefering their Honour to life, or all the glittering Glories of the Univerſe; no proſpect of Earthly happineſs has been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Charm it from them, as will appear.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42968:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Celdrana,</hi> a Maid of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> being Endowed with admirable Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which occaſion'd a Troop of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as it were to Beſeige her; each deſirous of enjoying ſo fair a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, offering what might content a large Ambition, but in vain; for ſuch were the Chaſt reſolves of the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Virgin, that the largeſt proffers could make no impreſſion on her mind; but perceiving her ſelf continually preſſed by her importunate admirers, to ſhun their importunity, ſhe private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdrew, and leaving them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in their loves for want of the bright <hi>Idea</hi> they ador'd, ſhe hid her ſelf in a ſolitary Cell ſurrounded with a multitude of Graves, where after a tedious ſearch being ſound, to the exceeding Joy of thoſe that ſought her; when asked the meaning why ſhe choſe a place ſo doleful, her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply was, <hi>Theſaurum Chaſtitatis Servo Inter Arentes Calvarias <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Nula Flamma Eurumpit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42968:32"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Amongſt the Dead my Chaſtiti's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</l>
                     <l>There I preſerve it in it's ſelf moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>No ſparks of luſt the drowſie Graves immure.</l>
                     <bibl>Cauſ. H. C. part <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Braſola</hi> of <hi>Diracchium,</hi> an Illuſtrious Maid, ſeiz'd by a Souldier, who was about to commit violence on that Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el that ſhe moſtly priz'd, told him that if he would ſpare her in that caſe, ſhe in recompence would reveal to him a Secret more valuable than Gold, ſuch a one, as would render him Victorious and Safe on all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by making him Invulnerable: the Souldier believes, flattering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that after he had obtained this Benifit, ſhe would be as much at his mercy as before; when leading him into a moſt delightful Garden, and after a tedious ſearch; taſting a Herb, that perhaps he had never ſeen before, ſhe with a chearful Voice told him it was the mighty Charm that would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42968:32"/>the force of Steel, and that he might be aſſured ſhe did not flatter, bared her Beautious Neck and offered the experiment at the hazard of her life; the Souldier by this being more confirmed, reſolutely gave the blow that gave her reſt in the wiſh'd Arms of Death.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Preſerving by that means her ſpotleſs Fame,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt her raſh Foe, who found himſelf to blame,</l>
                     <l>Confunded ſtood, with horror, grief and ſhame.</l>
                     <bibl>Lodov. Vives. Chriſt. Femin. Iſtit.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nor is the Storie related of the virtuous <hi>Euphraſia,</hi> a Virgin of noble Extraction in <hi>Nicephor, Eclez. Hiſt.</hi> unlike to this.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Where that <hi>Heroick Maid</hi> prefering, Death,</l>
                     <l>Before the loſs of Honour, loſt her Breath.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42968:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucia</hi> a lovely Virgin, who for the Excellency of her Beauty was ſought by divers, but out of an Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry love of Chaſtity, would not ſhew the leaſt inclination thereto; which, notwithſtanding, ſo Inflam'd a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Lord, who had great Command in the City where ſhe lived, that after many Eſſays, finding ſhe could not be won by Entreaty, he reſolved to take her by Force, and in order thereto, ſent divers Armed men to ſurprize her in her Fathers Houſe; who coming to the Gate and finding it ſhut, threatned to make a general Slaughter, and ſet all on Fire if ſhe were not delivered; ſhe to prevent the danger that might befall others, knowing the cruel Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of him that had ſent for her, came forth and demanded who it was they ſought, deſiring to know if any thing was in her power that would ſatisfie their Lord; <hi>Yeſs</hi> (ſaid they in a flout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner) <hi>your Eyes have Captivated him, he never can hove reſt till he has gained them;</hi> at which fetching a deep Sigh, ſhe deſired to retire, ſaying, <hi>ſhe would ſatisfie him in that particular;</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42968:33"/>which being ranted, ſhe went to her Chamber, and ſeeing her ſelf in a ſtraite, that ſhe either muſt uſe ſome extraordinary way, or her unſpotted Chaſtity would be Sacrificed to the Luſt of a Man ſhe hated, thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing her ſelf to her Glaſs; ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to utter her ſorrow: <hi>Ah! my Eyes</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>are you then guilty, I know the reſervedneſs and ſimplicity of your Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor have I in that kind any Remorſe of Conſcience; but howſoever be you, appear to me not Innocent enough, ſince you have kindled fire in the heart of a Man, whoſe hatred I ever eſteemed more than his love; Quench, Quench, then with your Blood the flame you have raiſed;</hi> whereupon with a hand piouſly cruel, ſhe forced h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Eye-balls from their bleeding Orbs, and ſent them to thoſe who waited for her, to bear them as a cruel pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent to their Maſter; upon notice of which, aſtoniſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded within himſelf, he fled to a Monaſtery, and there ſpent the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his days. <hi>Rad in Virido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Cauſ. H. C. part</hi> 1.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42968:34"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thus ſhe deform'd her ſelf to Gloom confin'd,</l>
                     <l>To ſave the lovely Beauty of the Mind.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acciolin</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> in the year 1253, ſurprizing the City of <hi>Baſſian;</hi> in which City <hi>Blanch Ruba</hi> fighting for the defence of her People, her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being before ſlain, ſhe was taken Diſarm'd, and violently drag'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conquerer; who Eyeing her admirable Perfections, with Preſents, Entreaties and Threats, for a time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to alure her to Laſcivious Embraces; but the noble <hi>Matron</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather reſolv'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> die, than to yield up her honour to the Murtherer of her Lord, ſound means whilſt thoſe were careleſs who had her in charge, to caſt her ſelf headlong out of the Gallery wherein ſhe was; by which fall, although ſhe greatly Bruis'd her ſelf, yet by the Care of the Phyſicians and Chyrurgeons ſhe recover'd, and then was caus'd to be bound Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, in a poſture, that the Luſtful <hi>Acciolin</hi> not regarding her Cries and Entreaties,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42968:34"/>forc'd her helpleſs Chaſtity. She <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſiring not to out-live the loſs of her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>onour, though her Friends comforted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er in the beſt manner; ſaying, <hi>ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>as Guiltleſs, ſeeing it was done by Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, contrary to her Conſent.</hi> When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e better to Accompliſh her deſign, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s well as ſhe could, diſſembled her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rrow, appearing by degrees to dry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p the Extraordinary flood of Grief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at ſlow'd from her Beautious Eyes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e deſir'd them one day to goe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er to the Monument of her Husband <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the often Viſitation of which is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary in many Countreys) being come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either, ſhe Entreated them to liſt up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſtone, that ſhe might ſee how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eath and his ſhort continuance there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad alter'd him; which ſtone o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a vaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eight, being rais'd on one ſide and rop'd up, ſhe under pretence of ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly viewing thoſe Reliques of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ortality, Leaped into the Tomb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here her dead Husband lay, pulling way at the ſame time the ſtay, which offer'd the ſtone to fall with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rce, that her Head being mortally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rus'd, ſhe ſoon died and was buried with her Lord. <hi>Lon. Thatre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42968:35"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>The latter loſs, beyond the Firſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd,</l>
                     <l>Her ſadded Soul, though Fate before had Tri'd,</l>
                     <l>In her dear Lord's miſhap, a Death to give,</l>
                     <l>But Chaſtity once gone, ſhe ſcorn'd to live.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Novellus Caronceus.</hi> Lord of <hi>Paria,</hi> falling in Love with a beautiful Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, a Citizens Daughter of <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia;</hi> and her Chiſtity not yeilding by fair entreaties to his lacivious deſigns, he cauſed her to be taken out of her Fathers houſe, and forcibly Raviſhed her, after which he not having found the Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſure he expected, by reaſon of her unwillingneſs, he Barbarouſly added a greater Cruelty, by cutting her in pieces, and ſending her Mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Limbs to her Parents: Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed at ſo great a wickedneſs, made their adreſs to the Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> in whom the horrour of the Fact, mov'd at once ſuch deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Compaſſion, that warring
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42968:35"/>on the murthering Raviſher, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ook him, and his two Sons, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey delivered into the hands of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xecutioner. <hi>Beard Theatre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So loud to Heaven for Vengance was the cry,</l>
                     <l>Of Virgin blood, and Injur'd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bright,</hi> Deputy or Sub-governour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a King of the <hi>Weſt Saxans,</hi> going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Progreſs, happen'd in the abſence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> one <hi>Beorn,</hi> a noble <hi>Saxon,</hi> to call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his houſe; whereas became a perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch eſteem with the King; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> as ſplendidly entertain'd, but all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> delicates were nothing pleaſing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conſideration of the beautiful Lady, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith whom he found (dinner ended) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> oppertunity (under pretence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmunicating ſome Secrets, he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> charge to her Lord,) to retire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to a private place, out of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g of the Servants, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al'd his wicked purpoſe, uſing many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>treaties, to oblige her to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>acency, but finding ſhe had rather
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42968:36"/>die than violate her Chaſtity, he threw her by force on a Couch and Raviſh'd her, after which, leaving her over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd in Tears, he with his reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue haſted thence. The afflicted La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy concealing as much as in her lay the ſhame that was done her, till her Lord came home, fell at his Feet with great Cries, declaring the Miſchief that had befallen her, ſaying, <hi>ſhe was altogether unworthy to name him her Huſband, ſince ſhe had been ſo ſhameleſsly abuſed, intreating him by all the former Ties of Love to revenge himſelf and her;</hi> which he not long after too ſadly ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, by being inſtrumental in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Danes,</hi> who made miſerable Havock of the Kingdom, ſlaying the Raviſher and moſt of the Forces he lead. <hi>Speeds Chron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wonderful were the Examples of the Chaſt Ladies in the <hi>Abby</hi> of <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> who by the Advice and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their <hi>Abeſs</hi> leaſt their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Beauties ſhould be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of looſing their honours, cut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> off their Lips and Noſes, at the time when the <hi>Danes</hi> made progreſs through
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42968:36"/>the Land with Fire and Sword, and by that means ſaving their Chaſtity, loſt their Lives; for the Barbarous Enemy finding it was done to croſs their purpoſe, cruelly put them to the Sword; doubtleſs not unhappy for them, who found thereby a ſpeedy way to the reward of their Piety. <hi>Speeds. Cron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Stand back <hi>Diana,</hi> in whom Fables tell,</l>
                     <l>The Sacred love of <hi>Chaſtity</hi> did dwell,</l>
                     <l>Yet cruel ſtill they Paint thee, for thine Eyes</l>
                     <l>They ſay, were pleas'd with Humain Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice;</l>
                     <l>Give place to theſe, whoſe Virtues ſhine more bright,</l>
                     <l>Than all the flames that on thy <hi>Alters</hi> blaz'd,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Chaſter Souls</hi> above the Stars took flight,</l>
                     <l>And for Deliverance their great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker prais'd.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="piety" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Piety.</head>
                  <p>In Piety and Love of ſacred things, this Sex is no ways wanting, as not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42968:37"/>to mention the Examples of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Holy Writ, many Hiſtories havi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the lively Monuments of unwear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Divotion, can furniſh us: nor ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they refus'd in moſt Ages, to lay do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> their lives with chearfulneſs for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſake of their Redeemer, Triumphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> with a Holy Joy in the Circling flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> bearing with a conſtancy and patien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> almoſt Inexpreſſible, all the Torme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Witty Horror could invent; nay ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> have griev'd to be depriv'd of ſuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Glory, and long'd with eager Zeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paſs through Tribulation, to the pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> where Crowns and Diadems a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lay'd up for the perſeverer, in faithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs till Death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eulalia,</hi> a noble Virgin of <hi>Portug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> diſpiſing all the proffer'd Glories th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> conſiſt in Tranſcient things, ſpent h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> time and care in heaping up a Treaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for her Soul; Sobriety and Mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> were her Attendants, and Diſcreti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Crown'd her Actions; a Zeal and F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Love to her Redeemer made h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fearleſs of danger, knowing his ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>port is all-ſufficient; and ſo continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe, increaſing in Grace and Virt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:42968:37"/>when Hell ſtir'd up it's wicked Engins to oppoſe the flouriſhing Goſpel, when the Heathens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>harras' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Church, than was it ſhe appeared moſt conſtant and devout, reſolving to ſuffer any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction for him that had redeemed her with his precious Blood; and when the Chriſtians were commanded to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Sacrifice to Devils, this Couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Virgin by her Prayers and Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, encouraged them to be ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the Faith, and not to give the Tempter ground, Praying dayly in the preſence of the Heathen; which her Parents, who loved her entirely, perceiving and fearing ſhe might fall under the puniſhment of the Rigorous decree, ſent her to their Countrey Houſe, diſtant from the City, and watched her there, leaſt ſhe ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape; but ſhe deſirous to poſſeſs a Crown of life, brooked not that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, but found means to leave it; and being ſometime after preſented to the <hi>Roman</hi> Prefect, a man that Thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after Chriſtian Blood, ſhe boldly own'd her Faith, aledging ſhe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to lay down her life for his ſake,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42968:38"/>from whom ſhe had receiv'd it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which reſolute perſiſtance in that rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> made him rage to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Exceſs, that without regard to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Birth, Years or Tender Beauty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> commanded the Executioner to diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate her Joynts, and then with Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Beaſts Claws tore off her Fleſh, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe regardleſs of her pain, was praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> God for counting her worthy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> After this ſhe was tortur'd with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iron Grate, and had her Virgin Brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Seer'd with flaming Torches, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fir'd her Hair that had till that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed her Modeſty; when find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> her labouring Soul upon the Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe Breath'd it forth in praiſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Maker. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Go <hi>Pious</hi> Maid, may your Exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> be,</l>
                     <l>Prais'd and admir'd to all poſterity!</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Palm</hi> is hers, nor can ſhe mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Crown,</l>
                     <l>Who for the ſake of <hi>Chriſt</hi> her life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> down;</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:42968:38"/>
                     <l>No Mixture, Crown of Pearl, of Gold and Cares,</l>
                     <l>Such as below an Earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch wares,</l>
                     <l>But a bright <hi>Diadem</hi> of Beaming Stars.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agnes,</hi> an Honourable young Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, being accus'd of profeſſing the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> and not denying it, when Interogated by the Judge, he threatned her with moſt Exquiſit Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, unleſs ſhe would Worſhip the Gods of the Heathens; but Arm'd with a <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> ſhe told him, <hi>ſhe fear'd no Tortures, as being willing to ſuffer all manner of Torments, even Death it ſelf, for the ſake of him that was able to raiſe her at the laſt day:</hi> Well ſaid the Judge, though you value not the Pain, yet I doubt not, but you have a great eſteem for your Virginity and Chaſtity, and it is my intent to thruſt you into the Stews, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Sacrifice to our Gods; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſhe perſiſted to inveigh againſt their pretended Deities, uſing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42968:39"/>many Arguments to convince the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of his Error, which made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wicked Fellows urge him to put the Beautiful Virgin into their poſſeſſion, that they might uſe her at their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which occaſioned her to tell them, <hi>that Chriſt was not forgetful of thoſe that are his, neither would he leave her deſtitute of his help and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but would be always ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend Modeſt and Chaſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins;</hi> and thereupon turning to the Judge, ſhe told him, <hi>He might freely bath his Sword in her Blood, but ſhould no: defile her Body.</hi> She had no ſooner utter'd theſe words, but ſhameleſs as he was, he commanded ſhe ſhould be bound ſtark Naked to a Poſt at a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a ſtreet; whereat the greateſt part of the People being ſorry and aſham'd, to behold an Innocent Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the tender Bloom of her Age expoſed to ſuch Ignominy: Some turn'd away their Heads, and others hid their Faces as they paſs'd by; but one impudent Fellow Scoffing at the helpleſs Maid and Gazing on her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs in deriſion, was blaſted with a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42968:39"/>flaſh of Lightning, and thereby loſt his ſight; upon which ſignal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe Sung praiſe to god for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring her in her diſtreſs: of which the Judge having notice, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Executioner to diſpatch her; who coming towards her with his drawn Sword, ſhe was nothing daunted, but on the contrary greatly rejoyc'd, ſaying, <hi>O this is he that I love and fain would meet, and not longer to protract my deſire, I will willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Sword in my Boſome. O Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, vouchſafe to open the Gates of Heaven to a Soul that ſeeketh thee,</hi> and then Kneeling down as well as her confinement would permit, ſhe had her Head ſtricken off; her Soul through that wide Wound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inding a paſſage to Eternal Reſt. <hi>Celebrate her praiſes, O ye Virtuous amongſt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and let not ſuch Chriſtian Examples enter into the Gloomy Region of Obliveon.</hi> Nor leſs deſerves the Memory of the Virtuous <hi>Eugena,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Philippus,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who died under the Heathen Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Sacred Profeſſion, by moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42968:40"/>Exquiſit Torments, but with a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage out-facing the Terror of Death. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon, &amp;c.</hi> A hundred more than theſe I could name, but having promis'd Brevity, I ſhall goe on to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Embelliſhments of the Sex.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>And ſince Fame's Enſigne's thus far born, unfurl'd</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Virtues, tell that muſt oblige the World,</l>
                     <l>Your worthy Names ſhall next in order ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Who from Oblivion with a Giving hand,</l>
                     <l>Brought Charity the Glory of the Land.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="liberality" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Liberality.</head>
                  <p>In this caſe I ſhall Inſtance but two Examples of Female <hi>Liberality,</hi> which ſtand as Monuments of that Sexes Generoſity.</p>
                  <p>The moſt virtuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Mary Ramſey,</hi> once Wiſe to Sr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Ramſey,</hi> joyning with him after his Death, Aſured in Land 243 pound <hi>p. Annum</hi> to <hi>Chriſts-Hoſpital</hi> (that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Charity and ſeminary of good
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42968:40"/>Education, to the uſes following, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Schoolmaſter of <hi>Hempſtead</hi> Annually twenty pounds, to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Uſher of <hi>Chriſts-Church</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually twenty pounds, to ten poor Widdows, beſides Apparel and Houſes Annually twenty pounds, to two Poor, <hi>viz.</hi> a Man a Woman during life, to each fifty-three Shillings and four Pence, to two Fellows in <hi>Peter Houſe</hi> in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and four Scholers yearly forty pounds, to St. <hi>Bartholomews Hoſpital</hi> ten pounds, to St. <hi>Peters,</hi> the Poor in <hi>London,</hi> St. <hi>Andrews <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſhaft,</hi> St. <hi>Mary Wolnoth</hi> ten pounds, to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, Ludghte,</hi> the <hi>Compters,</hi> ten pounds, to <hi>Chriſts Hoſpital,</hi> after the Expiration of certain Leaſes there will come p. Annum, one hundred and twenty pounds, to ſix Scholars in <hi>Oxford</hi> twenty pounds, to ſix Scholars in <hi>Cambridge</hi> twenty pounds, to ten Maimed Soldiers twenty pounds, for two Sermons two pounds, to the Poor of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Pariſh fifty Shillings, to the Poor of the Company of <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> yearly ten pounds, ten Poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Gouns, ten Poor Soldiers Coats,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42968:41"/>Shoos and Caps. All theſe to continue Annually. <hi>Willets Synopſ. Papiſ. p.</hi> 1229.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. <hi>Alice Owen</hi> founded an Hoſpital and Free-School at <hi>Iſlington,</hi> gave to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> Library at <hi>Oxford</hi> two hundred pounds, Founded one Fellow-Ship and Scholar-Ship in <hi>Emanuel Coledg,</hi> to <hi>Chriſts Hoſpital</hi> ſixty pounds, to give twelve Pence Weekly to the Poor of <hi>Iſlington</hi> ſixty pounds, thirteen Shillings and four Pence ſhe gave to Beautifie the <hi>Cloiſters in Chriſts Hoſpital,</hi> to a School-houſe at <hi>Edmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> twenty pounds, to the Pariſh of <hi>Condover</hi> in <hi>Shrop-ſhire</hi> fifty pounds to buy a great Bell, the Building of Alms-houſes for ten poor Women, and the purchaſing the Lands lay'd to it, coſt her one thouſand four hundred and fifteen pounds, and the Building the Schools there three hundred ſixty one pounds; ſhe gave likewiſe certain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Sums of Moneys to Preachers not Benificed, and to the Priſons in her life time, by her laſt Will twenty pounds yearly to <hi>Iſlington</hi> School, to Preachers thirty five pounds, to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42968:41"/>Pariſh of <hi>Baſiſhaw</hi> twenty pounds, to the Priſons eight pound, to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Brewers</hi> in Linnen, Plate and Money one hundred pounds, the Sum Total of the Money, not reconing the Annuity of twenty two pounds, Amounts to about two thouſand three hundred and twenty pounds; a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Extraordinary in a private Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman; yet this ſhe did out of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Zeal, to promote Learning and relieve the Poor, though at her Death ſhe had twenty two Children, and Childrens Children, for all which ſhe plentifully provided. <hi>Willet's Synopſ. Papiſme P.</hi> 1240.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Theſe great Examples who'd but imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</l>
                     <l>Treaſures lay'd up in Heaven's a vaſt Eſtate;</l>
                     <l>A Mine that no profuſeneſs can Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt,</l>
                     <l>And will repay ten thouſand times the coſt.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="humility" type="virtue">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:42968:42"/>
                  <head>Of Humility.</head>
                  <p>Nor does Humility ſhine leſs bright even to a wonder in the <hi>Softer Sex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Humility the Baſts, on which reſt</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Blooming actions that muſt make us bleſt;</l>
                     <l>Great pattern of true worth, which do's ſubdue</l>
                     <l>The ſterneſt Foe, and make his love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>In this caſe we find Famous Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Holy Writ; as <hi>Sarah, Rachel, Leah, Ruth</hi> and many more, who thereby not only had immediate Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings confer'd upon them, but render'd themſelves worthy Examples to all Poſterity. How many Virtuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies might I number in Hiſtories of divers Nations, would the intended Brevity admit a further Enrolement of their Names, who have wholly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted themſelves to Humility, the true ground of Generoſity and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, even ſuch, as in an Ocean of Worldly Proſperity have rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered they were Duſt, and that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42968:42"/>Earthly Riches, and the Fond Aplauſe of flattring Paraſites, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their enforc'd Eloquence could render them no other, as for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Daughter to a King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Wife to <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> of <hi>Tharengia,</hi> amidſt the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties wherewith her Court abounded, was ſo wonderfully affected with the Sence of Humility, that often remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home with her Maids. ſhe put on her meaneſt Apparel, ſaying, <hi>ſhe would never uſe any other Ornaments, when it ſhould come to paſs that the good and merciful Lord ſhould put her into a condition wherein ſhe might more freely diſpoſe of her ſelf.</hi> When ſhe went to her Divotion in publick, not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Greatneſs, ſhe would rather chooſe to Kneel amongſt the Poor Women than the Ladies of the Court, as imagining it moſt acceptable to her Maker. After the Death of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band whom ſhe lov'd, ſhe retir'd from places populous, with few attendants, and in the end went on Pilgramage, giving to the Poor what came to her
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42968:43"/>hands, and Built for their Relief an Hoſpital, wherein ſhe Miniſtred to the Sick, and took extraordinary care they ſhould want for nothing; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent for to Return to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Court, ſhe made ſuch Excuſes, and uſed ſo many Entreaties, that ſhe kept her ſtation, prefering Humility before the Enjoyments of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Farewell thou great in mind, who doſt out-vie</l>
                     <l>In this thy State, of true Humility,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that Ambition toſſes to the Skie.</l>
                     <l>So ſafe upon the Beach, the Gentle Swain</l>
                     <l>Beholds the trouble of the ſwelling Main,</l>
                     <l>And by contentment do's doſe dangers ſhun,</l>
                     <l>Into whoſe Arms the greedy Saylers run.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="patience" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Patience.</head>
                  <p>Nor is Patience, though ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracters have aledg'd the contrary, leſs admirable in Woman-kind: what wonderful Tryals has the Sex under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42968:43"/>even to admiration, not only in the loſs of Subſtance and a reduction to Poverty, loſs of deareſt Relations, and the like (but with an admirable conſtancy and ſtrmneſs of Mind) the moſt unjuſt and undeſerv'd Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments not mov'd nor diſorder'd by the almoſt Unconquerable effects of Fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Anger.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>But ſtood their Ground againſt the ſtorms of Fate,</l>
                     <l>Nothing their brave Reſolves cou'd diſſipate,</l>
                     <l>Gaining a ſecond place to his great worth,</l>
                     <l>Whom <hi>Uz</hi> to admiration did bring forth.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nor is it amiſs to mention one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Example, by which the Reader may gueſs at the reſt. In the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth <hi>French</hi> King, divers Licentius villains getting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhead Innocent Blood, Plunder Houſes, and commit many other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, amongſt the reſt, one whoſe Name was <hi>Dure,</hi> a very proper Name
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42968:44"/>for ſuch an Inexorable Ruffain, Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with many Curſes and Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Houſe of one <hi>Agnes</hi> a virtuous Widdow, and caſting a Cord about her Neck, drag'd her about till ſhe was almoſt ſtrangled (ſhe not in the leaſt complaining) and then letting her come a little to her ſelf, demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where her Money was; to which with a compos'd Countenance ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>ſhe had no more than a</hi> French <hi>Penny,</hi> which made him Rage exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and again repeat his cruelty in draging her about; but perceiving ſhe was unconcern'd at this, he put hot Eggs under her Armpits till they were Scorch'd and Bliſter'd extreamly; yet ſhe not ſo much as complain'd, but was more concern'd at the Impious Blaſphemies he utter'd than at her own pain. After that finding her Arm'd with Patience to a Miracle, he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to throw her from the higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Steeple in the Town; yet fearleſs of that Danger, ſhe Reply'd, <hi>If you throw my Body never ſo low, you cannot hinder my Soul from aſcending into Heaven.</hi> The Wretch by this wonderful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42968:44"/>of Mind not yet being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, ſtop'd Lime and Urine into her Mouth, which ſhe indur'd as the reſt; when finding he could no ways prevail he left her. <hi>Clarks Mart.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="steadfastness" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Steadfaſtneſſ.</head>
                  <p>To this may be Added, the Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and unſhaken Steadfaſtneſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſome women have receiv'd Death, and for Inſtance, two of our own Nation were moſt Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p>Queen <hi>Ann,</hi> one of the Wives of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and Mother to the Renown'd Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> upon the ſuppos'd falſe Accuſations of ſome Envious Perſons, who look'd upon her Greatneſs with eyes Aſcance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſentenc'd to Death, as ſhe was lead to be Beheaded in the Tower, eſpying one of the Kings Privy Chamber, ſhe call'd him to her; <hi>and Commend me</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>to the King, and tell him, He is conſtant in his courſe of Advancing me, for from a private Gentlewoman he made me a Marchioneſs from a Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs a Queen, and now that he hath left no higher degree of Worldly Honour for me, he hath made me a Martyr.</hi> Bak. Chron. P. 408.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:42968:45"/>
                  <p>Leſs admirable was not the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Patience of the Learn'd, Wiſe and Pious <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> a Lady of Royal Extraction; who for the guilty greatneſs of others, who againſt her Will advanc'd her to the Seat that was not her right, was in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> together with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band the Lord <hi>Guildford</hi> Condemned to die, during the reſpite. Doctor <hi>Fecknam</hi> was ſent to tell her ſhe muſt prepare her ſelf to die the next day; which Meſſage ſo little diſpleaſed her, that ſhe ſeem'd rather to rejoyce at it. The Doctor being earneſt with her to Embrace the old Religion and leave the new. She Anſwer'd, <hi>She had no time to think of any thing, but preparing her ſelf for God by Prayer.</hi> The Doctor ſuppoſing ſhe had ſpoken this, that ſhe might have ſome longer time of life, obtain'd of the Queen a further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of three days, and gave her to underſtand as much. Whereat ſhe with a Smilling Countenance reply'd, <hi>You are much deceiv'd, if you think I had any deſire of longer life: I aſure you, ſince the time you went from me, my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42968:45"/>life has been ſo tedious to me, that I long for nothing ſo much as Death; and ſince it is the Queens pleaſure, I moſt willingly uudergo it.</hi> Bak. Chron. P. 458. Nor was the Countenances of theſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alter'd on the Scaffold, till Death had turn'd their Lovely Faces to a deadly Paleneſs. Neither was the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at all diſcompos'd, when ſhe ſaw her Husband, whom ſhe Entirely lov'd, brought into her apartment Headleſs, as having the ſame morning been Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted a little before. <hi>Holingſheads Chron,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Such is the ſtrength of Mind ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bear,</l>
                     <l>That Death's Pale Terror can't infuſe a Fear.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>To theſe we might joyn the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>African</hi> Queen, though in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Method. The Relation thus,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophoniſba</hi> Queen of <hi>Numidia,</hi> &amp; Wife to King <hi>Syphax,</hi> upon the overthrow of her Husband, by <hi>Scipio</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul, yielded her ſelf up to <hi>Maſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſa</hi> an <hi>African</hi> Prince and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42968:46"/>of the <hi>Romans,</hi> Entreating him that ſhe might not be put into the power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate; he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to be her Protecter, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration fo her amazing Beauty, Marri'd her, having been contracted to her before her Marriage with <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phax;</hi> but it coming to the Ears of <hi>Scipio,</hi> he let him underſtand that the <hi>Romans</hi> had a Title to her Head, and that ſhe was a miſchievous Enemy to the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore requir'd him not to commit a great offence upon little reaſon. The King confounded within himſelf at this news, Bluſh'd and Wept for a time; but in ſine, promis'd to be Govern'd by <hi>Scipio,</hi> he went to his Royal Pavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, where having given his ſorrow vent, he call'd a truſty Servant, and by his hand ſent a Cup of Poiſon to his Beloved <hi>Sophoniſba,</hi> with theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, <hi>viz. That gladly he would have had her to live with him as his Wife, but ſince they who had power to hinder him of his deſire, would not yield there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, he had ſent her a Cup that ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld prevent her falling into their hands alive,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42968:46"/>willing her to remember her Birth and high Eſtate, which would direct her to take Orders for her ſelf.</hi> At the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Meſſage and Potion of Death, the Couragious Queen nothing daunted, reply'd, <hi>That if her Huſband had no better Preſent for his new Wife, ſhe muſt accept of this,</hi> Adding, <hi>ſhe might have died more honourable if ſhe had not Wedded ſo late before her Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> and thereupon drunk off the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Potion that bereav'd her of her life. <hi>Reighs Hiſt. World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Great thoughts long ſtrugl'd in her Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Till fear of Bondage, fear of Death ſurpreſt,</l>
                     <l>And that her Birth and Nobleneſs might be</l>
                     <l>An argument, ſhe ſcorn'd Captivitie,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe could die, ſhe let the <hi>Romans</hi> ſee.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And to ſay ſomewhat further much to the ſame purpoſe, a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron falling in Travel in Priſon, where ſhe was confin'd by the Perſecutors,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42968:47"/>upon the Account of her Religion, Expreſs'd ſome ſence of Sorrow; which being over-hear'd by her Enemies, they demanded if in that caſe ſhe was ſo ſenſible, what would ſhe be when ſhe came to the flames? <hi>Ah!</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I ſuffer this as a miſerable woman, under thoſe ſorrows that are lay'd upon me for my ſins; but then I ſhall ſuffer a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a Chriſtian for the ſake of Chriſt.</hi> Camer. Oper. Subſiſiv. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So different is the cauſe of Pain oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> found,</l>
                     <l>That what ſome think the moſt, the leaſt do's wound.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="modesty" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Modeſty.</head>
                  <p>Nor is the Wonderous, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming and ſeemly Modeſty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſome are poſſeſs'd, a leſs Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than what has been premis'd.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A Virtuous Modeſty do's Beauty grace</l>
                     <l>And make the Charms more lovely i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> each Face;</l>
                     <l>It makes the Roſes with the Lillies joyn,</l>
                     <l>The ſweet Carnation with the Geſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine:</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:42968:47"/>
                     <l>Nay further yet, it do's a Factor prove,</l>
                     <l>To barter hearts and trade in chaſteſt love:</l>
                     <l>Nothing more winns, there's nothing ſooner can</l>
                     <l>Than Female Modeſty, alure Fond Man.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And this Sex exceeds not only in Action, but in Speech and Gueſture: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome having choſen rather to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe ſevere Puniſhments, than to do, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r be Concious of any Immodeſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Martia</hi> Daughter of <hi>Varo,</hi> one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e braveſt Female Wits of her time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing skill'd in divers Arts, but more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urious in that Excellent one of Limn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g to the life; yet no entreaty or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard could prevail with her to por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ay or paint the Counterfait of a Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Woman Naked, leaſt thereby ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ould offend againſt the Rules of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſty; ſo concious was ſhe, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a thing moſt Innocent in its ſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt in ſhould meet with a wrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ruction, or ſhe therein give a bad
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42968:48"/>Example to others. <hi>Cauſ. Treat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Paſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor only in Life, but as we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſay, in Death it ſelf has this R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> been obſerv'd, as appears by the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Olimpias:</hi> For <hi>Caſſander</hi> having co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her to be ſlain, as ſoon as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Executioner ſent to diſpatch her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> inform'd her of his Meſſage, ſhe to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſpecial care ſo to wrap up her ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> her Robes, that when ſhe ſhould fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no part of her Body ſhould be diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, but what might beſeem a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Matron. And in the like man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the Wife of <hi>Pantheus,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doom'd to Death by <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> King <hi>Aegypt. Fulgoſ. l.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſlo</hi> in his Travels tells us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Young Gentlewoman in <hi>Japan,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by accident breaking Wind as ſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tended at the Table, was poſſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with ſuch a ſence of Shame, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately hiding her Face, ſhe depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo far reſented that Indecen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe as altogether undeſirous to ſurv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it, in a Rage bit off one of her Nip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> which inflaming her Breaſt, ſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:42968:48"/>her to the heart with a mortal Pain, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſo ended ſhe her days. <hi>Mandelo's Travels, L.</hi> 2. <hi>P.</hi> 190.</p>
                  <p>And yet ſtranger are the effects of Modeſty, as it appears in the ſtory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Mileſian</hi> Virgins, who out of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d humour, were many of them poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs'd with a deſire of laying violent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands on themſeves by ſtrangling; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd although they were narrowly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atch'd by their Friends, yet ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f them found opportunity to effect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>; which made their Parents attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ute it to the Divine diſpleaſure, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere at a loſs which way to appeaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he offended Deitie: When one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Sages</hi> propoſed a Remedy, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t firſt was ſuppos'd Indeſicient, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rov'd an Expedient to prevent that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſorder; which was, <hi>That every Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d who ſo Violated her life, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> a ſpectakle of Deriſion, be carry'd Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d through the Principal City;</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing confirm'd by a Decree, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear of the ſhame after Death wrought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> effectually, that for the future they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſiſted from that unadvis'd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mely Expulſion of Life, Modeſty in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42968:49"/>that caſe having a greater ſway with them than the fear of Death. <hi>Cauſ. H. C. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>L.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aluilda,</hi> the Beautiful Daughter of <hi>Suiardus</hi> a King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> was poſſeſs'd with ſuch Baſhfulneſs, that for the moſt part ſhe Veild her Face as not being willing to expoſe her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Bluſhes, which commonly flulſh'd in her fair Cheeks, at the ſight of Man. <hi>Olaus. Mag. L.</hi> 5. <hi>C.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So much the ſence of Modeſty ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wrought,</l>
                     <l>That it has Wonders to Perfectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> brought;</l>
                     <l>A ſpark it is of Native Innocence,</l>
                     <l>Dwelt with our Parents e're they gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> offence,</l>
                     <l>E're ſhameleſs ſin in <hi>Eden</hi> did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="temperance" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Temperance.</head>
                  <p>For Temperance this Sex has been wonderfully Eſteem'd in all Nations as the Enemy of Luxury, which is one main reaſon why they are generally more Healthful than Men; and exceed them in the Prologation of their lives,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42968:49"/>affecting in all things a Modeſt Neatneſs and Decency, Order and Comlineſs being their proper Attribute.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nature in this Expreſſes them refin'd,</l>
                     <l>In choiceſt Molds ſhe caſts fair Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-kind.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>As for the powerful effeſts of their Charming Beauty, they are ſo Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally known, eſpecially to Lovers, that in vain it would be to Endeavour a fuller ſatisfaction; than each <hi>Idea</hi> of hoſe Angelick Creatures forms in the Fancy of him by whom ſhe is admir'd; but ſeeing Fame has been Lavish in ſpreading o're the Univerſe, the Amazing perfections of her, whoſe Rape <hi>Troy</hi> Mourn'd in Tears of Blood, and in whoſe hard recovery the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Greece</hi> was loſt. Nor leſs is my intent to tell of <hi>Aegypts</hi> far fam'd Queen, whoſe matchleſs Beauty Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated him, to whom great <hi>Rome</hi> and all the World bended low.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of the above nam'd Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties was Daughter to <hi>Ledea,</hi> ſnatch'd from her Mothers Arms almoſt in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42968:50"/>her Infancy, by the War-like <hi>Theſeus,</hi> then the Glory of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but afterward reſtor'd a ſpotleſs Virgin, and Marri'd to the renown'd <hi>Menelaus,</hi> King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving after the firſt delights, ſo great a Treaſure under ſlender Gaurds, she was ſorpriz'd by <hi>Paris</hi> Son of <hi>Priam,</hi> and in an unhappy hour covey'd to <hi>Troy,</hi> a Famous City in the Leſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Aſia,</hi> but for that Rape raz'd by the enrag'd <hi>Grecians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Lady was of Complection fair her Skin ſoft as the down of Swan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Enrich'd with charming whitneſs, the Round of her Face, inclining to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Oval, her Eyes black, and not the largeſt ſize, poſſeſs'd all that could b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deſir'd in Lovelineſs, quick they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with Mildneſs, and ſo full of Love, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with a ſingle Glance they darted into the coldeſt breaſt all the flame tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſparkled in themſelves. Her Mouth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> way inferiour to her Eyes, was ſmall and ſhut with Lips that bore the pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Virmillion; in it's natural frame i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſented an Object not to be para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd for Beauty, and when it open
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42968:50"/>either in ſpeech or ſeemly laughter, it not only expoſed rows of Ivory, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieing Orient Pearls, but afforded thoſands of new Charms, her Hair like curling Amber dangled on her Snowy Shoulders, her Hands and Arms were long and final, white as poliſh'd Ivory, or the curious Alablaſter, yet more taking by the Azar ſtreams that wantonly Meandr'd through their tempting ſoftneſs, in her fair Cheeks, Roſes and Lillies ſtrove for Maſtery, and in ſine, Fame will have her ſuch a lovely Frame, ſo perfect in each part, that 'tis no wonder if Love, to which no Law at all times can ſet bounds, conquering the reaſon of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Prince, made him at any hazzard co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet ſuch a Treaſure.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A Treaſure, had it been a lawful Prize,</l>
                     <l>Which might have made his Towring fancy riſe,</l>
                     <l>Above the Soar of other Earthly Joys.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>As for the Beautious <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> ſhe was Daughter of <hi>Ptolomeus Auletes,</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:42968:51"/>King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and after the death of her Father, and Brother <hi>Ptolomeus, Cajus Julius Caeſar,</hi> for the Love he bore her, made her Queen of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> her Magnificence and Excellent Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being thus deſcribed by <hi>T. May,</hi> in his Second Book of Continuation, Anexed to <hi>Lucan's Pharſalia,</hi> where relating the entertainment ſhe made to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he thus begins.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Great <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> Miſtreſs of the State,</l>
                     <l>To give the Conquering Author of her Fate,</l>
                     <l>High Entertainment, to his Eye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play's.</l>
                     <l>Th' Aegyptian Wealth, in ſuch Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ways,</l>
                     <l>As might Excuſe even <hi>Rome</hi> and make the Riot</l>
                     <l>Of her degenerate Senate ſeem the Diet.</l>
                     <l>Which th' Antient <hi>Curii</hi> and <hi>Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> us'd,</l>
                     <l>Not what her <hi>Aſian</hi> Vistories Infus'd.</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:42968:51"/>
                     <l>The Gorgeous Pallace with ſuch Luſter ſhown</l>
                     <l>As wealthy Kingdoms near their ruin grown.</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s'd to expreſs, which ſhew the preſent crimes,</l>
                     <l>And ſpeak the Fortune of precedent times.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Caeſars</hi> Eyes in all that wealthy ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Which he ſo lately had beheld before</l>
                     <l>No pleaſure find, nor with delight viewes he</l>
                     <l>The Golden Roofs, nor precious Imag'rie.</l>
                     <l>Rich <hi>Eben</hi> Pillars, Boards of <hi>Citron</hi>-Wood,</l>
                     <l>Which on their carved <hi>Ivory</hi> Treſſels ſtood.</l>
                     <l>Nor curious Hangings do his Eyes admire,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Cleopatra</hi>'s Beauty and Attire,</l>
                     <l>Did quite Eclipſe thoſe Objects, and out ſhone,</l>
                     <l>All other ſplendors, on her looks alone</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:42968:52"/>
                     <l>His Eyes are ffx'd, which though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held before,</l>
                     <l>The more he views, do Raviſh him the more.</l>
                     <l>All other Objects looſe at ſecond ſight.</l>
                     <l>But Womans Beuaty breeds the more delight</l>
                     <l>The ofter ſeen; he views that Snowy neck,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Golden treſſels, which no Gems can deck.</l>
                     <l>The Wealth ſhe wore about her ſeem'd to hide,</l>
                     <l>Not to adorn her native Beauties Pride.</l>
                     <l>Though their bright Pearls from the <hi>Erithrnean</hi> Shores,</l>
                     <l>From all th' <hi>Aſſirian</hi> Lakes, the wealthy Stores</l>
                     <l>Of Silver, Ganges, and <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> ſhone,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Aegypt's</hi> Eaſtern Iſles, the Gold green ſtone,</l>
                     <l>And chearful Emralds gather'd from the Green</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Arabian</hi> Rocks, were in full ſplendor ſeen.</l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:42968:52"/>
                     <l>Pale <hi>Onyx, Jaſper,</hi> of a Various die,</l>
                     <l>And Diemonds darken'd by her bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Eye.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Saphires</hi> blew, by her more <hi>Azure</hi> Veins,</l>
                     <l>Hung not to boaſt, but to confeſs their ſtains.</l>
                     <l>And bluſhing Rubies ſeem'd to looſe their Dye,</l>
                     <l>When her more Rubie Lips were move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by.</l>
                     <l>It ſeem'd (ſo well became her what ſhe wore)</l>
                     <l>She had not rob'd at all the Creatures Store.</l>
                     <l>But had been Natur's ſelf there to have ſhow'd,</l>
                     <l>What ſhe on Creatures cou'd or had beſtow'd.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="learning" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Learning.</head>
                  <p>But not to proceed further, in a perfection that is ſo Perſpicuous; I ſhall paſs from it, to relate that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Beauty, which more compleats the adornment of the Mind, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in the Soul, delates it ſelf not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42968:53"/>only to the praiſe of the poſſeſſor, but the benefit of others; and in the firſt place, inſiſt upon the admirable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections Women have attain'd to in Learning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tabiola</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Matron, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſirous to Improve herſelf in the Knowledge of Sacred things, adicted her ſelf to Learning; and ſo profited therein, as to gain that eſteem amongſt the Learn'd which caus'd St. <hi>Jerome</hi> to dedicate a Book to her Intituled <hi>De V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſte Sacerdotali Mercela Romana,</hi> and was mentioned in divers of his <hi>Epiſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Alexander Sforza,</hi> had improv'd her ſelf in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her Indefatigable Induſtry, that upon the ſuddain, and without any Premeditation ſhe was capable ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to diſcourſe upon any ſubject, either <hi>Theological</hi> or <hi>Philoſophical</hi> and was moreover ſingularly read in the works of St. <hi>Jerome, Ambroſs, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, Lactantius</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi> In Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie ſhe was admirable, and ſo fluent that with her Extempory Conceits ſhe attracted the Ears of the Learned, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42968:53"/>this Facility of hers is reported to be Innate, as proceeding freely without force or affection. <hi>Heywood of W.</hi> Nor has the Ingenious Sex been leſs ſeen in Phyloſophy.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>In deep Phyloſophy were women Verſt,</l>
                     <l>Through thoſe dark ſecrets womans Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>As will appear in the Example of <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queen of the <hi>Palmirians,</hi> who after the death of <hi>Onedatus</hi> Govern'd that Kingdom of <hi>Syria,</hi> Her the <hi>Romans</hi> took Captive and brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> but there for her admirable skill in, and knowledge of that Divine Science, ſhe was not only Pardon'd, but alow'd a Pallace upon the Banks of the River <hi>Tiber,</hi> and was there Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected with the ſame Regard as the <hi>Sophies</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> were wont. Being at any time Invited to hear Publique Orations, ſhe would never appear, but Arm'd with her Shining Helmet on her Head, a purple Mantle flowing on her Shoulders, Button'd with pretious Gems. But above all, ſhe was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42968:54"/>skill'd in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Tongues; and in the like Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe inſtructed <hi>Hermolaus</hi> and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> her Sons, and is mention'd by <hi>Volaterran</hi> as a moſt accompliſh'd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>One in whoſe Wiſe, in whoſe Heroick Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Greatneſs and Learning did together reſt.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>In Oratory women have been found skilful Proficients, as appears in many Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amaſia</hi> a virtuous <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſed of a Crime, and ready to undergo the Sentance of the Pretor, ſhe in the mideſt of a great confluence of People, ſtep'd up and pleaded her own cauſe ſo effectually, and with ſuch Eloquence, that by the publique ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, ſhe was Aquitted of the Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Layd to her charge, and in that great Affair, uſed ſuch Decency and Modeſty, that ſhe got to her ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Sir-name <hi>Androgyne. Val. Max. L.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:42968:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> the Daughter of Queen <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> when the <hi>Roman</hi> Matrons had a large Fine impoſed on them by the <hi>Tribuns,</hi> and the Lawyers fearful to undertake her cauſe, ſhe as the Advocate of her Sex, boldly plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it before the Triumuirate, with ſuch chearfulneſs and ſucceſs, that the greateſt part of that Impoſition was remitted.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So that 'tis plain, the greateſt uſe oth' Tongue</l>
                     <l>Which to the fair Inchanting Sex be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belong,</l>
                     <l>Is no to Schold, as <hi>Black Detractors</hi> ſung.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Not unaptly are the Muſes placed in the Feminine Gender, appropriate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themſelves the names of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſince the Sex has been in paſt Ages, but more immediately in the preſent Inſpir'd, with raptures of Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to a degree of charming the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but before I proceed to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, it will not be amiſs to ſpeak a word on the behalf of Poetry, nor
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42968:55"/>can they be better deliver'd, than in the Language of the <hi>Muſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>How e're inſpir'd the Soul with Rapture frought,</l>
                     <l>Has dark confuſion into order brought,</l>
                     <l>Bough Nations ſtrangers to Civility,</l>
                     <l>Have been reclaim'd by ſacred Poetry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Morality has ſprung, when it has Til'd</l>
                     <l>Ith' breaſt before with Barbariſme fill'd</l>
                     <l>A power it has to Charm the Teſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> bold,</l>
                     <l>Clam reſtleſs Thoughts and ruged Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Mold.</l>
                     <l>Though ſome may ſay in Fables 'tis profuſe,</l>
                     <l>Take off the Veile, we Golden Truth produce.</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Diamonds</hi> e're they'r Popliſh'd loc not bright,</l>
                     <l>And unlight <hi>Tapors</hi> dart no Beams <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> light,</l>
                     <l>Into the devious Darkneſs of the Night</l>
                     <l>So Poetry to thoſe, who from it's sphe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are diſtant far, do's not it's ſelf appear</l>
                     <l>'Tis queſt by thoſe, as Ruſticks gueſt Star.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:42968:55"/>
                  <p>But to the purpoſe, Poets are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to be the firſt Revivers of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and Morality amongſt Men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Phyloſophers, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute it to themſelves: And further, that <hi>Apollo</hi> found out the Muſes, and brought <hi>Mercury</hi> acquainted with them; for which good turn <hi>Mercury</hi> invented the Harp and gave it to <hi>Apollo,</hi> which in the <hi>Moral</hi> ſence is, that Poetry and Rhetorick goe hand in hand, and that a Poet cannot be Excellent unleſs he be a good Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, nor a Rhetorician accompliſh'd without he be a Poet; though of late the younger Brother has gotten the advantage of the Elder as to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preferment.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Great <hi>Orators</hi> delight on Earth to ſhine,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Poets</hi> only aime at things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And in the latter as well as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Women were famous, as will appear by the following Example.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Minerua,</hi> ſeigned to be the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42968:56"/>of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> for her excellent Fancy in Poetry, was eſteem'd by the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents a Goddeſs; but moſt likely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſe ſhe was inſpir'd as we call it, with Excellent Fancy, and was held in high eſteem amongſt the <hi>Athenians.</hi> Fam'd next to her are the <hi>Corinna's,</hi> of which there are recon'd three, <hi>viz. Corinna-Thebana,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodorus,</hi> and <hi>Procratia</hi> Scholar to <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> She in five ſeveral Contentions bore away the Palm from <hi>Pindaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Eſteem'd the Price of <hi>Lyrick</hi> Poets, and publiſh'd five Books of Epigrams, and is mention'd by <hi>Propertius. Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Theſpia</hi> greatly admir'd for her Works, but more eſpecially taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by <hi>Statius.</hi> The third liv'd in the Regn of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and is much taken notice of by <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sappho</hi> for her Poetry was Famous, and was as <hi>Elianus</hi> affirmeth, the Daughter of <hi>Scamandronius,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> of <hi>Ariſtan, Suidas,</hi> and other <hi>Greek</hi> Writers ſay there were two of that name, the one call'd P. <hi>Erixa,</hi> a much Celebrated Poeteſs, who flouriſh' in the time of <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus,</hi> and by
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42968:56"/>many is Imagin'd to be the Inventer of <hi>Lyrick</hi> Verſes. The other was call'd <hi>Sappho Mitelaena,</hi> who publiſh'd many Poems amongſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> though ſomewhat Extravagant, yet for her Ingenuity had the honour to be ſtil'd the Tenth <hi>Muſe:</hi> and of her <hi>Antipater Sidonus</hi> thus writes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When Sappo's Verſe ſhe did admiring Rerad,</l>
                     <l>Demanded whence the Tenth <hi>Muſe</hi> did proceed.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Teleſilla</hi> had a wonderful Fancy in this kind, whereby ſhe obtain'd the Sir-name <hi>Poetria,</hi> and was no leſs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable for Wiſdom, Beauty and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, being Born of Noble Parents: ſhe in her Youth was adicted to much Indiſpoſition of Body, and therefore Inquir'd of the <hi>Oracle</hi> concerning Health: Anſwer was return'd her, that ſhe ſhould apply her ſelf to Study. Nor long was it e're ſhe complying with the advice of the <hi>Oracle,</hi> but had her Health reſtor'd, and attain'd to a wonderful perfection in Learning;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42968:57"/>but eſpecially improv'd to admiration in the Divine Fancy of Poeſie, and thereby gain'd ſuch an Eſteem, that when <hi>Cleomines</hi> King of <hi>Sparta</hi> ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon the <hi>Argives</hi> in a Hoſtil manner, ſhe inſpir'd the <hi>Argive</hi> Women with ſuch Courage, that after their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands fled and were many of them ſlain, they renew'd the Battle, her ſelf Leading the <hi>Van,</hi> Routed the <hi>Spartans,</hi> and return'd Victorious into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                  <p>To theſe I may add that Phoenix of Virtue, the Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> of whom I have made mention before, though in a different nature. This Lady no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exceeding Eighteen years at her death had never the leſs improv'd her ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to a degree that ſhe was skilful in the Languages, in Phyloſophy and Divinity; but above all, Excellent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Divine Poetry, and may be ſaid to be the Epitomie of Perfection.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:42968:57"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>To theſe I many more might add, whoſe worth</l>
                     <l>Their works <hi>(than I)</hi> twice livelyer can ſet forth?</l>
                     <l>Our age abounds with Female wits, who find</l>
                     <l>The ſacred <hi>Muſes</hi> to their Fancies kind.</l>
                     <l>With rich conceits their larger hearts are fill'd,</l>
                     <l>Which riſing thence, and in the Brain diſtill'd,</l>
                     <l>To all the World Harmonious numbers yield,</l>
                     <l>In all the taking ſtrains of Poetry,</l>
                     <l>Cadence or Rapture of the firſt degree.</l>
                     <l>A lively Lantskip drawn of Humble Swains,</l>
                     <l>Feeding their Flocks upon the Flowry Plains;</l>
                     <l>Through which Meandring Rivers ſmoothly run,</l>
                     <l>By ſhades Imbowring, ſhelter'd from the Sun;</l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:42968:58"/>
                     <l>In whoſe warm Beams the frisking Lambs do play,</l>
                     <l>And then to full ſtretch'd <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dders take their way,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Rural Muſique Charms the fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day.</l>
                     <l>To theſe they add the Mirtle Crowned Hills,</l>
                     <l>Where Golden Ceres all the Valey fills,</l>
                     <l>Or 'midſt the Pride of Gaudy <hi>Flora</hi> ſing,</l>
                     <l>A joyful Welcome to the Blooming Spring;</l>
                     <l>When ſtrugling long, ſhe breaks from Winters arms,</l>
                     <l>And ſmilling courts the Sun with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Charms:</l>
                     <l>How when he falls in <hi>Thetis</hi> watry Bed,</l>
                     <l>She on a Bank of <hi>Violets</hi> lays her head,</l>
                     <l>And ſighing o're the world, her Tears do's ſhead</l>
                     <l>In ſilver drops, untill <hi>Aurora</hi> fair</l>
                     <l>Opens her Gates, and do's reſtore her Dear:</l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:42968:58"/>
                     <l>Tell how ſhe's loſt in Summer, who does Twine</l>
                     <l>The Bluſhing Roſes with the Geſſamine,</l>
                     <l>To make thoſe pleaſing Bowers where Lovers play,</l>
                     <l>Not penetrated by the Eye of day.</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a one, if we may Credit fame,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Archiſe</hi> dally'd with the ſtarey Dame:</l>
                     <l>Or tell of <hi>Autums</hi> Burthen Rhind with Gold,</l>
                     <l>Fluſht with Vermillion, or in Purple fold;</l>
                     <l>Whilſt 'neath their weight the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd Branches bend,</l>
                     <l>And they their Fragrance to <hi>Pomania</hi> ſend.</l>
                     <l>Thus they can Tune their Harps, but ſlightly ſtrung,</l>
                     <l>As when Great <hi>Maro</hi> to <hi>Maecenas</hi> ſung;</l>
                     <l>But if to higher ſtrains they Tune their Lyre,</l>
                     <l>Such as are fit for Great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Eare.</l>
                     <l>A ſceen of war and <hi>Hero's</hi> mighty deeds,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt to the Trumpet dance the bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſteeds;</l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:42968:59"/>
                     <l>There lively they preſent the threatning <hi>Vann,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of either <hi>Hoaſt,</hi> before the Fight began</l>
                     <l>The horrid ſhock, when wars gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ridg is ſtorm'd,</l>
                     <l>And how the Battle in all parts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> form'd.</l>
                     <l>Till when the fury riſes to it's hight,</l>
                     <l>Who well deſerves, who ſaves himſelf flight;</l>
                     <l>Who in a Rank unbroken, fierceſt flin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>His Leaden Thunder-bolts on lightnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wings;</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Tiphons</hi> flame does vault <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> field with fire,</l>
                     <l>And drowns the Cries of thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> there expire;</l>
                     <l>Who ranges furious through the dire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> taque,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Courage brings the flying S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers back,</l>
                     <l>Who Brandiſhing aloft his glitteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Blade,</l>
                     <l>Wide waſting ſcatters thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Invade,</l>
                     <l>Who ranges looſly, who makes good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Who diſobeys, who fights as by comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:42968:59"/>
                     <l>Who braveſt dyes, who with his dying breath</l>
                     <l>Threatens the Foe, and ſmiles upon Grim Death,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Clouds of ſmoak bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> redneſs hide,</l>
                     <l>Who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to ſee the field with ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dy'd.</l>
                     <l>Tell who gave way, who firſt 'twas left the field,</l>
                     <l>Who in the fight, who in purſuit were kil'd,</l>
                     <l>What ſpoiles were taken in the doubtful war,</l>
                     <l>Who is o'recome, and who the conquerer,</l>
                     <l>What glorious Trophies are affix'd on high,</l>
                     <l>As a memorial of the Victory;</l>
                     <l>Theſe they oblige their Muſes to relate,</l>
                     <l>Or lively Paint a drooping Nations fate.</l>
                     <l>Then why in this ſhould woman looſe her praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Why ſhou'd ſhe want deſerved wreaths of Bays.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:42968:60"/>
                  <p>Further in this caſe I may Inſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Famous <hi>Sybils,</hi> who are not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> counted Poets, but Propheteſſes, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fore it will not be amiſs in this plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to give a brief account of them, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> has been handed down by paſt Ages to the preſent, and tranſlated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſdorus</hi> ſaith, the word <hi>Sybil</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> name of place and office, derived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Syos,</hi> which ſignifies a Deitie and Bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoughts of the number of theſe <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bils</hi> Antients Write different. <hi>Aeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> will have but four, <hi>viz. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thraea, Samia, Egyptia</hi> and <hi>Sardim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Arctina</hi> agrees with <hi>Iſdore</hi> in the <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology</hi> of the Word, and likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Numbers ten, and aſcribes them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> following places and names, <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Perſia, Libia, Delphica</hi> as Born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Delphos, Omeria</hi> of <hi>Italy, Erithraea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Babylon, Samia, Cumae, Helleſponti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Phrygia</hi> and <hi>Alburnea. Cumae</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that brought Books to <hi>Tarquinius Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> which ſpake of the <hi>Roman</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; and how ſtrangely ſoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> theſe were inſpir'd, they told ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Truths; and as the Antients affir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> expos'd their Propheſies in Verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:42968:60"/>but for Brevities ſake I ſhall only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoſe that were fulfil'd in the Conception and Birth of our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybilia Perſica</hi> Born in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eld more Antient than the reſt; who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aving Expreſs'd the moſt Material things, relating to the ſeveral Ages of the World, till the Year of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed Saviours Incarnation: Thus speaks,
<q>
                        <l>In which Year, of a <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhall be Born,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> Crown'd with a wreath of <hi>Thorn;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Him</hi> the ſeventh age ſhall follow and Extend</l>
                        <l>Till the worlds frame diſolve, and time ſee end.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybilia Libia,</hi> by ſome call'd <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>roe,</hi> was held to be the Daughter of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ollo,</hi> Sir-nam'd <hi>Prima,</hi> and is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted by ſome the firſt Inventer of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eroick Verſe, and of our Bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>viour thus held to Propheſie.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:42968:61"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>A <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a <hi>prophet,</hi> all theſe three</l>
                     <l>Shall meet in one <hi>Sacred Divinity,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall be to Fleſh Eſpous'd, O who can ſcan</l>
                     <l>This Miſtery, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting <hi>God</hi> with <hi>Man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When this rare <hi>Birth</hi> into the world ſhall come,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He</hi> the great God of <hi>Oracles</hi> ſtrikes <hi>Dumb.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nor may it be amiſs, to ſet down how exactly the two laſt lines were fullfil'd: For the very day wherein our Bleſſed Saviour was born, one ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Reſponſe of the Oracle had this Anſwer.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Me Purus Habreus Superum Rex Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere Tecta</l>
                     <l>Hac jubet, et cacas Noctis remeare Sub umbras;</l>
                     <l>Ergo ſilus Aris tu nunc diſcendit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> noſtris.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:42968:61"/>
                  <p>And may be thus Engliſhed.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A Hebrew Child King of the heavens high,</l>
                     <l>To leave theſe Alters, has Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me</l>
                     <l>To Nights dark ſhaddows and to final Woe.</l>
                     <l>Thou therefore ſilent from our Alters go.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And ſince that time it is obſerv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey remain'd mute.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybilia Delphica,</hi> was by ſome call'd <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aphne,</hi> and ſaid by ſome to be Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Tyreſias,</hi> ſhe having fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Wars of <hi>Troy,</hi> proceeds to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us of our Bleſſed Saviour.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>An Angel ſhall Deſcend, and ſay, Thou bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi> Hail;</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt conceive, bring forth, yet be A Virgin Without fail.</l>
                     <l>Three gifts, the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> to thy Son, Shall tender with much Piety,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Myrrh</hi> to a Man, <hi>Gold</hi> to a King, And <hi>Inſence</hi> to a Deity.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:42968:62"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Cumaea,</hi> alſo called <hi>Cimmonia,</hi> is held to have been one of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſes to <hi>Apollo,</hi> born in <hi>Cuma</hi> a City of <hi>Aetolia,</hi> and ſpake thus, in relation to our Bleſſed Saviour.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Th' Antient of days ſhall then ſubmit to time,</l>
                     <l>The meeker yeild him ſelf to new Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</l>
                     <l>The Deity and Godhead moſt Sublime</l>
                     <l>Take ſhape of Man, to ranſom every Nation.</l>
                     <l>Die to make others live, and ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Crime</l>
                     <l>Committed, from the round World<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> firſt Foundation.</l>
                     <l>Take on himſelf, as low as hell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending</l>
                     <l>To win Man, Heaven upon his Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> depending.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Samia,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rophile,</hi> took the name of <hi>Sama</hi> fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lſle of <hi>Samos,</hi> the place of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> birth, her Predictions were theſe.</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:42968:62"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>The World ſhall to ſix thouſand years expire,</l>
                     <l>By water once, but then Deſtroy'd by Fire.</l>
                     <l>The firſt two thouſand Void, the next the Law,</l>
                     <l>The laſt two under the <hi>Meſias</hi> Aw, And as repoſe by Sabath is expreſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> all things ſhall then have reſt.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Cumana,</hi> by ſome called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nalthaea</hi> having Propheſied of the great Revolutions, and Succeſſions of the Monarchies of the World, ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the Glories of <hi>Rome,</hi> She comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o her Predictions of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iour.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Great <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall then look high,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe proud Towers, from their hills ſhall brave the ſky,</l>
                     <l>And overlook the world, in thoſe bleſt days,</l>
                     <l>Shall come a King of Kings, and he ſhall raiſe</l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:42968:63"/>
                     <l>A New Plantation, and though great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er far,</l>
                     <l>In Majeſty and pow'r, yet in the day,</l>
                     <l>So meek and humble he ſhall daign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> pay</l>
                     <l>Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet thence hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py he,</l>
                     <l>VVho ſhall his ſervant, or his ſubje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> be.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Helleſpontica,</hi> was otherwiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> called <hi>Marrinenſis,</hi> and as ſome aſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> derived her ſelf from <hi>Troy,</hi> her Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions being theſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When <hi>Atlas</hi> ſhoulders ſhall ſupport Star,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Pondrous weight he never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> before;</l>
                     <l>The Splendor of it ſhall direct fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Far,</l>
                     <l>Kings, and the Wiſeſt Men, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Light to adore,</l>
                     <l>Peace in thoſe days ſhall floriſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtern War</l>
                     <l>Be baniſh'd Earth, Mankind to reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:42968:63"/>
                     <l>Then ſhall the Eaſtern Monarchs, Preſents bring,</l>
                     <l>To one, a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a <hi>Prophet, and a King.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Phrigia,</hi> as moſt are of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, was no other than <hi>Caſſandria,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Pryam</hi> King of <hi>Troy,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his Queen, She foretold the deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> but was never credited, but ſpeaking nothing of our Bleſſed Saviour, I ſhall paſs by her Predictions, though they axactly came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o paſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Tiburnia,</hi> ſo call'd of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er <hi>Tiber,</hi> was otherwiſe call'd <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urnia</hi> or <hi>Albania,</hi> from the City <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a,</hi> the place of her Birth. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orted of her, that the <hi>Romans</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g about to Deifie <hi>Auguſt Caeſar,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anded her advice, who after three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ays faſting, before the Alter where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Emperor was preſent, after many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yſterious words, Miraculouſly ſpoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ncerning our Bleſſed Saviour, upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſuddain the Heavens ſeem'd to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en; and <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaw a Beautiful Virgin
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42968:64"/>ſtanding before the Alter, holding an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Infant in her Arms, whereat affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he fell on his Face, and heard a Voice, ſaying, <hi>This is the Alter of the Son of God,</hi> in which place a Temple was after built and Dedicated to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and call'd the Alter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Heaven. This <hi>Polichronicon</hi> Aſſerts and quots St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for his Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 8, <hi>cap.</hi> 24. Her Predictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> our Saviour were theſe, after ſhe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> recited divers wonders of the World<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which I willingly omit.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>What at theſe Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es ſtands the World amaz'd,</l>
                     <l>And hath on them with Admir ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Gaz'd.</l>
                     <l>Then Wonder when the Troubl'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> apeaſe</l>
                     <l>He ſhall deſcend, who made them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> made theſe.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Europica</hi> was ſo call'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that her particular Region or place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Birth was not known, nor is ſhe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> counted amongſt the Ten, but adde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and her predictions were theſe.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:42968:64"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>VVhen the great King of all the world ſhall have</l>
                     <l>No place on Earth, by which he can be known.</l>
                     <l>VVhen he that comes all Mortal men to ſave,</l>
                     <l>Shall find his own life by the world o'rethrown.</l>
                     <l>VVhen the moſt Juſt, Injuſtice ſhall deprive,</l>
                     <l>And the great Judge be Judged by his own.</l>
                     <l>Death when to Death, a Death by Death hath given,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall be op't the long ſhut Gates of Heaven.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Aegypta</hi> was likewiſe Added <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Ten, ſhe propheſied on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umber Three, and having reckoned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>any things Exiſtent in that nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us proceeds.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>But which of us obſerve the ſacred <hi>Trine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Three Perſons in one God-head Sole Divine,</l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:42968:65"/>
                     <l>That Individual Eſſence, who dare ſcan,</l>
                     <l>VVhich is, ſhall be, and e're the world began</l>
                     <l>VVas in Eternity, when of theſe thru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>One of that moſt Inſcrutable <hi>Trinity</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The ſecond perſon, <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> ſhall E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomb</l>
                     <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Majeſties</hi> within a <hi>Virgins Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Man, true God, ſhall to that be <hi>Trine Link,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>True Light</hi> ſhall ſhine, and <hi>Falſe Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> be Extinct.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybila Aerithraea</hi> was Born in <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and was Daughter to <hi>Beroſius</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Famous Aſtrologer; ſhe propheſie of the <hi>Greeks</hi> that came to the Sie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Troy,</hi> defined the places when<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they came, and how long the Sie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would laſt, mentioning in her Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r,</hi> and how that he ſhould wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of thoſe Wars partially, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Affection, and not the Truth; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in this manner propheſied ſhe of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bleſſed Saviour.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:42968:65"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>The time by the great <hi>Oracle</hi> aſſign'd,</l>
                     <l>VVhen <hi>God</hi> himſelf in pity to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall from the Heav'n decend, and be Incarnate,</l>
                     <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ring the world a <hi>Lamb</hi> Imaculate,</l>
                     <l>And of himſelf in wiſdom thinks ſo Meet,</l>
                     <l>VValks on the Earth with three and thirty Feet;</l>
                     <l>And with ſix Fingers, all his Subjects then,</l>
                     <l>Though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>King Mighty,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Number twelve, with theſe war ſhall be try'd</l>
                     <l>Againſt the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Pride.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Humility</hi> ſhall quell, the ſharpeſt Sword</l>
                     <l>VVith which they <hi>Fight,</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Sacred Word</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Eſtabliſh'd upon <hi>Earth,</hi> which Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</l>
                     <l>Once lay'd, ſhall be Divulg'd to every <hi>Nation.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="painting skill" type="virtue">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:42968:66"/>
                  <head>Women skill'd in Painting.</head>
                  <p>By the Words Feet and Finges are to be underſtood Years and Months. And thus I conclude the propheſies and predictions of the <hi>Sybils;</hi> which if truly theirs, and by their being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd down through ſo many hands, they have been neither added to, nor deminſhed, it remains doubtful whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was in the power of any Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit to divulge ſuch ſacred truths ſo long before they came to paſs; or if it was, by this we may ſee that the Devils themſelves were conſtrain'd to fore-tell what they fore-ſaw would be the Ruine of their Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>As Limning or Painting comes the neareſt to Poetry; the one Expoſing things Lively drawn to the Eare, and the other to the Eye. I ſhall Incert the dexterity of ſome Women, skill'd therein.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thymarete</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Myca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> was eminent in this Art: and amongſt other curious pieces drawn to the life, ſhe drew that Maſter-piece which fill'd the Beholders with admiration, <hi>viz.</hi> The picture of <hi>Diana,</hi> which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42968:66"/>hung up in the Temple of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> ſhe being accounted the beſt Artiſt the World had afforded to that time, and flouriſhedin the time of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> King of <hi>Macedon. Pliny l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Irene</hi> was Daughter to <hi>Crantinus</hi> (a man Famous in this Art) ſhe by often obſerving her Father, ſo wonderfully profited herein, that ſhe drew the Counterfait of a Beautious Virgin of the City of <hi>Eleuſina</hi> ſo to the Life, that after it had been a long time prais'd and admir'd, it was plac'd amongſt the Rarities, to be admir'd by ſucceeding Ages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lala Cizice</hi> Daughter to <hi>Marcus Varo,</hi> practiſed the uſe of the Pencil in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Art of Limning attain'd to ſuch perfection, that ſhe drew her own picture to the Life by the help of a Looking-glaſs: She alſo uſed a ſharp pointed Quill, call'd <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> with which ſhe curiouſly cut in Ivory, as in theſe days <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> do in Silver or Copper, and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended above all the Virgins of her time for nimbleneſs and dexterity of hand, none ever equaling her in quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42968:67"/>and for Fancy and Curioſity ſhe exceeded <hi>Sopylon</hi> and <hi>Dionyſus,</hi> who otherwiſe found none that might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with them: and leaſt the cares of Marriage ſhould hinder her herein, ſhe choſe to ſpend her days in a ſtate of Virginity. <hi>Heywoods Hiſt. W.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thus art i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſpir'd, Ingenious women can</l>
                     <l>Equal, if not Exceed the skill of man.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="weaving skill" type="virtue">
                  <head>Women skill'd in Weaving.</head>
                  <p>In curious Webs the Sex claimes propriety as an Art attributed to their Ingenuity, and in this many have been Famous, as <hi>Arachue</hi> of <hi>Lydia,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arus,</hi> who wrought ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that ſhe is Fabled to be turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto a Spider by <hi>Minerua,</hi> with whom ſhe contended for precedency. <hi>Penelope</hi> the Chaſt wiſe of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> who made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> her Employment, during her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds being abroad in the <hi>Trojan</hi> Wars, and his wandering at Sea; nor would ſhe be perſwaded by any means to Marry, during his twenty years Abſence, neither by her Parents nor the Nobles that came to Court
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42968:67"/>her, although ſhe was Inform'd her Husband was dead, but when they were ſo Importunate that ſhe concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they would compel her, ſhe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them, that ſhe might make an end of her Web, and then ſhe would conſent to Marry, but inſtead of finiſhing it, what ſhe Weav'd in the Day ſhe Unravel'd in the Night, and by that means delay'd them, till her Husband came home, and freed her from their Importunity, from whence the Proverb aroſe, <hi>Penelopes, Telum Texere;</hi> or <hi>Labour-in-Vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Olimpias</hi> and <hi>Livia;</hi> were exceeding dexterous herein, and although great Queens, yet they ſet places apart, in their Pallac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to Exerciſe this Art, and Inſtructed others in it, the Firſt Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Garment for her Son, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, and the Second, a, Mantle for the Emperor <hi>Octavian Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> her Husband, <hi>Alex.</hi> ab Alex. <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tanaquil</hi> Wove a Kingly Garment, or Imperial Robe woven quite through with Rays, and Flame; or Streams of Gold, which Robe, <hi>Servius T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llus</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:42968:68"/>often wore, when he ſat in the <hi>Capital,</hi> on the Judgment Seat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auſonias</hi> ſpeaks of one <hi>Sabina,</hi> not only Excellent in this Art, but likewiſe in Poetry, whoſe Memory he left to poſterity, in the following Epigram.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>If thou affect a Purple Robe,</l>
                     <l>Woven in the <hi>Tyrian</hi> ſtain,</l>
                     <l>Or if a title well Inſcrib'd,</l>
                     <l>By which thy Wit may gain.</l>
                     <l>Behold her Works Impartialy,</l>
                     <l>And Cenſure on them well,</l>
                     <l>Both, one <hi>Sabina</hi> doth profeſs,</l>
                     <l>And doth in both Excell.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="courage" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Courage &amp; Conduct in War.</head>
                  <p>Thus much being ſaid of the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Virtues, and other things relating to the Beautious Sex; it will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to ſay ſomething of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Courage and Conduct, relating to War, or Warlike Exploits.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Women have ſhin'd in <hi>Camps,</hi> as well as <hi>Courts,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>More ſeen in <hi>Mars's</hi> Armes, than <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſports.</l>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:42968:68"/>
                     <l>Charging through Bloody Fields, to purchaſe Fame,</l>
                     <l>And raiſe the <hi>Trophies</hi> of a Warlike Name.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nor is it Fabulous, as ſome have I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd, that there was, if it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue not to this day, a Nation of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, call'd <hi>Amazons,</hi> deſcended from the <hi>Scythians,</hi> who upon their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's being ſlain in Battle, Aſſum'd the Government. Vowing never more to ſubmit to the Tyranny, as they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd it of man, but to keep as many as were ſufficient for Propagation, and to ſend the Super-numerary Males that ſhould be, when brought up, to ſeek their Adventures in other parts of the World, and not return, unleſs recall'd, upon pain of Death, and by this means they Encreas'd in Pow'r and Strength, uſing themſelves to all manner of Military Exerciſe. Their Firſt Queens mention'd, were <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſia</hi> and <hi>Lampedo,</hi> who Joyntly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, divided their People into two Armyes, and went to War by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42968:69"/>turns, after whom Succeeded <hi>Antiope,</hi> and <hi>Orythia,</hi> who by their Valour much Enlarg'd their Borders, the Fame of whoſe Valour it's ſaid, drew <hi>Hercules</hi> with an Army to Invade their Country, But having Experienc'd their mighty prowes, ſtood amazed, yet the <hi>Viragoes</hi> finding their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try waſted by the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſent to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillus</hi> King of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging they were deſcended, from that Nation, and therefore pray'd his Aide, who ſent his Son with a Gallant Troop of Horſe, but after a while, ſome diſſenſions arriſeing in <hi>Scythia,</hi> the Prince withdrew his Forces, yet the <hi>Greeks</hi> tyr'd with a Bloody and doubtfull War, though under the Leading of the moſt Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Captain that ever <hi>Greece</hi> boaſted, upon conſideration that <hi>Theſeus,</hi> a Noble <hi>Grecian</hi> ſhould have <hi>Hipolite,</hi> Siſter to theſe <hi>Amazonian</hi> Queens in Marriage, a peace was concluded, and the <hi>Greeks</hi> withdrew, having enough of <hi>Female Valour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the Aforementioned Queens Succeeded the Valiant <hi>Pentheſilaea</hi> who
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42968:69"/>came in Favour of <hi>Priam,</hi> or as ſome ſay for the Love of <hi>Hector</hi> to <hi>Troy,</hi> whil'ſt it was beſieg'd by the <hi>Greeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> with a Thouſand Ladyes, where after ſhe had perform'd many Vala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Exploits, and done all that true Valour was capable of performing, over-power'd by Number, and weak through loſs of Blood, ſhe was beaten from her Horſe, and ſlain by <hi>Achilles,</hi> or as ſome ſay, by <hi>Neoptolimus,</hi> and was the firſt obſerv'd to Fight with a <hi>Poleax,</hi> or wear a Shield in the form of a half <hi>Moon,</hi> and of her, <hi>Virgil</hi> ſpeaks, in his firſt <hi>Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>id,</hi> and may be thus in Engliſh,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pentheſilaea</hi> Mad, leads forth Her <hi>Amazonian</hi> Train,</l>
                        <l>Arm'd with their Moon'd-<hi>Shields,</hi> and Fights</l>
                        <l>Mid'ſt thouſands on the plain.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis apparent, theſe <hi>Amazonians</hi> continued till the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and though <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ras</hi> ſeems to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>irm that <hi>Alexander</hi> quite Subd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>'d their Nation, yet others ſay that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42968:70"/>that King ſending to demand Tribute of them, their Queen <hi>Minithra</hi> (or as ſome call her <hi>Thelaſtria</hi>) then Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned this anſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is great VVonder of thy ſmall Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, O King? that thou deſireſt to wage VVar againſt VVomen. If thou being ſo great a Conqueror, ſhould be Vanquiſh'd by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, all thy former Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours would be Eclips'd, and thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually branded with Diſgrace; but if our Gods, being angry with us, ſhould deliver us up to thy Mercy, what addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is it to thy Honour, to have Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qriſh'd weak VVomen.</hi> With which words <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſo well pleas'd, that he granted them Freedom, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>that VVomen ought to be Courted with fair words and not with</hi> Hoſtility. Whereupon the King deſireing to ſee her. She came to his Camp, where converſing together, about divers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of State, they ſeperated.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Amazonians,</hi> were by the <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> call'd <hi>Aeorpatae,</hi> which in their Language ſignifies <hi>Man-Killer,</hi> and the reaſon why this name is given, is becauſe they abjur'd the Society of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42968:70"/>Men, any more than was reaſonable for Propagation, <hi>Curtias Quintus</hi> in his fifth Book thus deſcribes their Habit. Their Garments (<hi>ſays he</hi>) cover'd not their Bodies round, their Right ſides were bare towards their Breaſt, their upper Robe which was Buckled or Button'd above, deſcended no lower than the Knee, one of their Breaſts they reſerved ſafe and untouch'd, with which they nouriſh'd Infants; but as for the other, which was the right, the growth of it was hindred by ſeering in the time of Child-hood, that with the greater dexterity they might uſe their Arms. <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſpeaks much of them, and amongſt other things (<hi>he ſays</hi>) to Encourage their Valour, they had a Law, that no Virgin ſhould enter into familiar Congreſs with Man, before ſhe had brought from the Field the Head of a ſlain Enemy.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>And thus the brave Viragos fierce in arms,</l>
                     <l>Train'd up in Camps, and us'd to hot alarms;</l>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:42968:71"/>
                     <l>Made all the Neighbour Nations ſtand in awe,</l>
                     <l>And Rul'd their Countrey by a Female Law;</l>
                     <l>In this we ſee that Pallas Burniſh'd spear,</l>
                     <l>Can with the Sword of Bloody Mars compare.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Not inferior to theſe was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd <hi>Camilla,</hi> Queen of the <hi>Volſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> This Lady in her Cradle gave token of enſuing Valour, for ſhe was not wrap'd in Softneſs, nor fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd by a Nurſe, but by her Father <hi>Melebeus</hi> with Milk of Hinds and wild Goats; nor did ſhe when come to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, adict her ſelf to what is uſual for women, but vowing Chaſtity, ſhe betook her to Hunting wild Beaſts, of whoſe skins ſhe made her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; her food for the moſt part was Veniſon, and her drink Water from the Fountain; and in this Aſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious and Chaſt life ſhe continued many years, but in proceſs of time the <hi>Volſcians</hi> for her Virtue and Valour
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42968:71"/>choſe her their Queen, and when the War happened between <hi>Turnus</hi> and <hi>Aeneas,</hi> ſhe brought her Troops into the Field in favour of the former, and there did wonders; but happy for <hi>Aeneas,</hi> as ſhe was Charging furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly on his Routed Squadron, a <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> watching his oportunity, ſhot her into the Breaſt with an Arrow; of which Wound ſhe dyed, and with her the Fortune of King <hi>Turnus.</hi> And thus <hi>Virgil</hi> in his ſeventh <hi>Aeniad</hi> ſpeaks, as I find it Tranſlated by <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>To their ſupply <hi>Camilla</hi> came, The Gallant <hi>Volſcian</hi> Laſs,</l>
                     <l>Who bravely did Command the Horſe, With <hi>Troops</hi> that ſhin'd in Braſs.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Atlantea</hi> was Daughter of <hi>Jaſus</hi> and <hi>Clymene,</hi> in her tender Age her Father caſt her out to a deſperate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, for no other reaſon than that ſhe was of the Female Sex; when a Shee-Bare more Compaſſionate than her cruel Parent, nouriſhed her in the Woods with her Milk, till ſome Huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42968:72"/>fortuned to come by, and caſting their Eyes upon her lovely Beauty, took her home and carefully brought her up: In her Youth ſhe adicted her ſelf to the uſe of Arms and Hunting wild Beaſts, till by her Swiftneſs and wonderful Courage ſhe grew Famous. She was wonderful Expert likewiſe in managing ſwift Horſes, turning Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots in the mideſt of their Careir, Wreſtling, throwing Darts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hunting the <hi>Callidonian</hi> Boar with many of the Noble Youths of <hi>Greece,</hi> ſhe was the firſt Wounded that furious Beaſt, on which occaſion <hi>Plautanus</hi> Cites her as an Example, as thus,
<q>
                        <l>As did the <hi>Meleagrian</hi> Girl, who in the <hi>Aetolian</hi> plain</l>
                        <l>Lay'd flat the Foaming Boar, and was the foremoſt of the train</l>
                        <l>That gave him bold Encounter, and as Ignorant of fear,</l>
                        <l>Notch't her ſharp Arrow, and the ſtring pluck't cloſe up to her Eare:</l>
                        <l>The firſt that day in Field, that Blood from the ſtern Monſter drew,</l>
                        <l>Bearing the honour, ſpoile and palm from all the Princely crew.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:42968:72"/>
                  <p>To theſe it will be convenient to add ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Viragoes, who in Conduct and Courage have not been Inferior to the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elphlelda,</hi> Siſter to King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, before the Conqueſt, was Wife to <hi>Etheldredus</hi> Duke of <hi>Mercia,</hi> ſhe affiſted her Husband in reſtoring the City of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> after it had been demoliſh'd by the <hi>Danes.</hi> After the death of her Husband, ſhe Govern'd his Principality Wiſely and Valiantly, Built many Cities and Towns, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired others, as <hi>Thatarn Brimſbury;</hi> ſhe Built a Bridge upon the <hi>Severn,</hi> and did many other famous things. This Lady having once endured the pains of Child-birth, refrain'd her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Bed, though not without his conſent; ſaying, <hi>It was unſeemly for a woman of her degree to Innure her ſelf to ſuch wanton Embraces, whereof ſhould enſue ſo great a pain and ſorrow.</hi> The <hi>Welſhmen</hi> heing unruly in thoſe days, ſhe tam'd them, and over-threw the <hi>Danes</hi> in ſeveral Battles; in Memory of whom <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth left this Epitaph upon her Tomb.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:42968:73"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Elphlelda,</hi> thou great in ſtrength and mind,</l>
                     <l>The Dread of men, and Viotteſs of thy kind;</l>
                     <l>Nature has done as much as Nature can.</l>
                     <l>To make the Maid, but goodneſs makes then M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>;</l>
                     <l>Yet pity thou ſhould'ſt change ought but thy mama,</l>
                     <l>Thou art ſo good a woman, and thy fame.</l>
                     <l>In that grows greater and more worthy, when.</l>
                     <l>Thy Feminine Valour much outſsineth men.</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Caeſars</hi> acts, thy noble d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</l>
                     <l>So ſleep in peace, <hi>Virago Maid</hi> fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Heywoods Hiſt. Women.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maud,</hi> Daughter to <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> the firſt, was Married to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, her Husband dying, ſhe had the Title of Empreſs, and her Father <hi>Henry</hi> cauſed the Nobility of <hi>England</hi>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:42968:73"/>to Swear Fealtie to her, as his Lawful Heir; but he dying, many left her, and took part with <hi>Stephen,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bulloin;</hi> when contending for her right, ſhe Fought many Battles with him, in which her Courage, Prudence and Conduct ſhin'd to admiration, and at laſt took King <hi>Stephen</hi> Priſoner, whom ſhe brought to <hi>London,</hi> the people every where, <hi>Ken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> excepted, owning her Soveraignty. Upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the King was priſoner, his Wife came to Ranſome him, and offer'd a Renountiation of his Claim to the Kingdom; but ſhe not hearkning to it, the People Mutined againſt her, which Oblig'd her to fly to <hi>Oxford,</hi> there to attend the Uniting of her ſcatter'd Forces; but being there hardly preſs'd by the Queen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that had Aſociated with her, ſhe caus'd her ſelf to Eſcape, being made a priſoner to be Coffined up as dead, and carryed to <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> her Brother <hi>Robert</hi> being at that time taken priſoner; and King <hi>Stephen</hi> ſoon after getting his Liberty, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd her in the City of <hi>Oxford</hi> from
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42968:74"/>
                     <hi>Michalmas day</hi> to Midd-Winter, at what time being ſtrain'd through want, ſhe Attired her ſelf in White, and by that means paſſing the Fenns cover'd with Snow, ſhe came to <hi>Wallingford Caſtle,</hi> and ſoon after had the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom put into the poſſeſſion of her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> Crown'd by the Name and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="loyalty" type="virtue">
                  <head>Of Loyal Women.</head>
                  <p>In Loyalty to their Prince, Women in all Ages have been unparaled Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and in that caſe <hi>England</hi> is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully Indebted to the Memory of that Extraordinary pattern of Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and unſhaken Fidelity Mrs. <hi>Jane Lane,</hi> whom no promiſe of reward, or the fear of looſing her own life could induce to betray her Soveraign; but rather with an undaunted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and never to be forgotten Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, ſhe Courted hazard and danger for the preſervation of his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, of ever Bleſſed Memory.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>To blot ſuch virtue, fond man ſtrives in vain,</l>
                     <l>For it like Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> purges off its ſtain,</l>
                     <l>And by it does a brighter L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtur gain.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:42968:74"/>
                  <head>The Introduction to the Reaſons and Arguments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THus far with an adventerous hand, I have portray'd the Virtues of the <hi>Fair Sex,</hi> in their many ſingular qualities, and yet intend not here to ſtop, but produce more ſollid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confirm their worth, Though there is nothing more nice and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate, than to Treat on the Subject of Women, eſpecially if we ſpeak to their advantage, for then it is ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd a piece of Gallantry or Love, the Extravigancy of good Humour, or the Ardent Feavour of an Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Paſſion; though certain it is that the moſt happy thoughts that can poſſeſs the labouring Minds of thoſe that would acquire a ſollid Science, after they have been vulgarly inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, may have reaſon to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have been taught aright or not, and labour ſtill to find a way at leaſt to a higher Improvement of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42968:75"/>what they but indifferently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. And in this caſe the Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of good Women, works won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the lofty Soul of Man, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things contemplated, more lovely and curious to the Eyes and Thoughts, or rendering us more pliable to Entertain a large eſteem of what the Wiſe have term'd a Sollid happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo thoſe that have but viewed the ſuperficies of Female Excellence, can no more be ſenſible of the highth of that perfection, than a Rude <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> of the inward Luſtre of an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſh'd Diamond found in it's Rockey coverture, amongſt the common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Earth. At a diſtance we behold the glorious Lamp of day, and though at once we well perceive it fills the world with heat and brightneſs, yet by reaſon of innumerable ſpaces 'twin it and the Earth, the Vulgar think in ſmall, and that a narrow room might eaſily contain that, which more than a hundred times exceeds in Magnitude the ſedentary Globe. Thoſe glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flames of Night, that move i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miſtick dances, and keep their orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:42968:75"/>o're the drowſie World; who that is Ignorant of Moral and Divine Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, would not take them for Shining ſparks or ſtudds, inchac'd in the blew Firmament as ſeeds of Light; when if they are not Worlds or Manſions of Coeleſtial Spirits, yet are they moſtly larger by many degrees than this which we Inhabit. Thus in caſe of Womens virtues Antient as the World, and Univerſal as Mankind, the Ignorant Indulge themſelves in ſloath and luck-leſs error, whilſt thoſe whom Heaven intruſts with larger Tallents, either hide them in a Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, or ſuffer Envy or Ingratitude to find a lodgment in their Souls, either to detract from that Eſſential good which God has plac'd in the faireſt Creatures, or ſhut their Eyes through wilful ſtubbornneſs, becauſe thy will not ſee, and by ſuch means be made to confeſs their ſtoick dulneſs or ſeverity. Great indeed is the Soul of Man, and comprehends more than the Univerſe: it's glorious Center being far above all hight, yet oft like Birds that fly too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear the Waves, the Damps of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſſneſs
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42968:76"/>ſlag it's Wings, and hinder it from ſoaring to thoſe Altitudes, where it may pry into abſtruſeſt things, from Vulgar ſight remov'd, and many times as inconſiſtent as the day with night, from what is fondly feign'd or imagin'd by thoſe Protoyps of Wit, who would at leaſt ſeem Wiſe, and yet many times they fall as ſhort of what they think, with Elevation they have ſcan'd, and look'd for fond Aplauſe for a conceited Merrit, as thoſe who through a Teleſcope ſuffer their Eyes to delude their better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by fancying large Countreys and Provinces, Cities, Rivers, Lakes, People, Beaſts and flying Fowl in the Moons ſpotty Globe; for ſhould we grant it was a World, and did contain all theſe, yet mortal ſight help'd by the greateſt Art or Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on brought to light, in the height of it's Improvement, cannot Penitrate ſo vaſt a ſpace to make diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things. Imaginations all! tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> too oft delude us, like the wandring Fire that dances, or ſeems to dance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the belated Traveller, whom fear
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42968:76"/>and darkneſs diſpoſſeſs of that reaſon which ſhould make him keep his way, obligeing him by fixing his dazl'd Eys on the Maetorious blaze, or unctious vapour, kindl'd by vehement Agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and kept from expanding by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viorning cold; to wander after a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding guide, which by his movei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g gains a motion through the yeilding Air; or like to thoſe that fancy by the Moons pale light, to ſee a Troop of Faires danceing to an Airey Melody, and Jocond on their Mirth Intent, whil't fear and Joy at once diſtracts his Reaſon, and in the heighth of a confus'd diſorder, wild Imagination, makes him think he ſees a walking Viſion, when Indeed deluſion repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents that which really is not. So oft has Error found a place, even where deep Wiſdom dwells, as well as in the Manſion of ſimplicity, and why then may not thoſe who have at leaſt pretended to the Study of Female Worth, and yet rendr'd ſo ſlender an account of it, be miſtaken in what's truly valuable in that kind, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhooting the Mark, or in not ſtating
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42968:77"/>it aright; as thoſe who cannot reach it, as well render it not only uninte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible, by over doing and not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it Perſpicuous in its native Sphere, as by debaſing, and Ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to leſſen it by meanneſs, and an ungrateful Contempt. <hi>Rome</hi> who worſhip's the Image of <hi>Jupiter</hi> Crown'd with Rays and Stars deck'd with Gold and Glittering Gems, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed no more a Superſtitious Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, than Fanatique <hi>Aegypt,</hi> a mean and covetous one, by Worſhiping Gods, in the likneſs of brute Beaſts, but to wave this dark diſcourſe I ſhall proceed to give my Sence in a Method ſuitable to the Subject.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:42968:77"/>
                  <head>Reaſons and Arguments for the Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul of <hi>Women,</hi> &amp;c. In Relation to <hi>Learning, Arts,</hi> and <hi>Sciences.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>THough Men may boaſt of their Wonderful Abilities, yet certain it is, the Fair Sex, way boaſt the like, eſpecially a Capacity of performing as much, ſeeing the Soul proceeds from one and the ſame Fountain of Life; and if we conſider the Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, what can we find in it, that may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in ought, being generally more lively and active than that of Man, as being made of a ſofter Contexture, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has not been wanting to frame the Cabinet of the Soul, to the beſt advantage, and has therein manifeſted her ſelf an excellent Miſtreſs, for a Creature fairer in Proportions and more Regular in every part ſhe never made; againſt this ſome will object that according to the Organs of the Body, as they are more or leſs ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of receiving the Influence of the Soul, which Enlivens and ſupports
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42968:78"/>the Body, is the party, or elſe ſay they, why may not a Child have as large an underſtanding as a Man? the Soul not being an Infant, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to ſo narrow compaſs, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not opperate, and this ſay they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears likewiſe in an Idiot, or a Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, by reaſon the Organs are Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or obſtructed, or confounded, by diſtempers, and conſequently the better part, though a Spirit is hinder'd in it's Motion and Office, and therefore give it as their Opinion, that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being of a colder and more watry Conſtitution then Men, have not Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans capable of giveing the Soul ſcope in it's operation, as the Bodyes of Men have, ſeeing they contain grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heat, which cauſes ſtrength and lar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſs of Body, more Vigour and Acttivity, more Acuteneſs and Solid Judgment, though had they a Womans Wit, which upon a ſuddain conception or ſwift turn, is many times found available, and ſometimes preſſerable to that of Man, yet it holds not throughout the Sex, nor is it at the beſt, capable of ſerious matters, or
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42968:78"/>to unlock the <hi>Arcanes</hi> of profound Sciences, and dive into Myſterious things, Occult and hid from the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ways of the World, and require a ſound Judgment, capable of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and weighing each particular. Should I grant that the Souls of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Idiots and Lunaticks, are under a reſtraint, and have not the pow'r to Act, as in other Caſes, as indeed it is true. Yet we ſee the ſame happens as well to the one Sex, as to the other, therefore that can be no Objection, but only to ſhew the Independency &amp; Obſtruction, of thoſe Effects, but where it is otherwiſe the caſe is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, for it plainly apears there are different Conſtitutions in either, all are not the ſame, in the one, nor in the other, for ſome men are Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, ſome Sanguine, ſome Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorick, and others Melancholy, and yet of all Conſtitutions, there have been ſome Famous for I earning, others in Arts and Sciences, ſome in Arms, and rare Inventions, and generally the Phlegmatick, are given to the Study of the Profoundeſt Sciences,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42968:79"/>What hinders then, that Women who participate of all theſe complections, &amp; undoubtedly have Souls of the ſame Exiſtence with thoſe of Men, that they may not be as Capable of procuring themſelves to be Regiſter'd in the Book of Fame, as thoſe who ſtile themſelves the Nobler Sex? As for that the Compoſure of the Mortal hindring the Immortal part in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it's office, is a poſition frive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vain, and makes more againſt thoſe that object it than for them, for it is often ſeen that in crooked and deform'd Bodies, Wiſdom chooſes to dwell, a Soul indued with more Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge perhaps than that which is found in a more ſtately fabrick of Fleſh and Blood; which Knowledge is wonderfully increaſed by Induſtry, Study and Labour; for although the Soul in it ſelf being a ſpark of the Divine light, is Immortal and a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet it is capable whilſt on Earth, of taking an Impreſſion by Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though nothing can fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it but God, from whom it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to whom it muſt return for its
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42968:79"/>reward of good or evil. <hi>The Body,</hi> (ſays the Wiſe-man) <hi>returns to the Duſt, but the Spirit to God that gave it. Ariſtotle</hi> was crooked and deformed, yet the World has not ſince produced a man of ſo Univerſal a Genius, ſo ſeen in all Arts and Sciences. As for the coldneſs of Conſtitution, that can be no hinderance, for it has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd that men of colder Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than many women, have Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Capacities of the <hi>Sanguin</hi> and <hi>Cholerick:</hi> What then may be the reaſon? why it is plain, Man having attain'd the upperhand in Rule and Power, claiming it by Birth-right as firſt Created, as much as in him lyes ſtrives to keep that ſtation as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, by endeavouring to keep the <hi>Softer Sex</hi> in Ignorance; and to Effect this, he uſes his utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to poſſeſs her with a belief of her Incapacitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, hat ſhe may not reach at things Sublime, and by compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending them, know the largneſs of her Soul. So the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to gain themſelves the more eſteem, and be adored by the unthinking Vulgar, had
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42968:80"/>all their miſtery in <hi>Hyroglyphicks,</hi> dark reſemblances, which perhaps them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſcarce underſtood: nor would they ſuffer any other Characters to paſs for ſignifications, leaſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by improvement in Learning might detect their falſeties, and grow Wiſer than themſelves. So the <hi>Turk</hi> will ſuffer no <hi>Printing</hi> in his large Dominions, leaſt the greateſt part whom he through Ignorance, holds as in a Chain of Slavery, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hiſtories of other Lands, ſhould find how much they are Abus'd. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when they made a Conqueſt of the Golden Mines, kept the knowledge of its value from the Native <hi>Indians,</hi> that they might not ſtrugle for it with an equal Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This is the main reaſon why men decline to Celebrate the praiſes due to the <hi>Softer Sex,</hi> and to let them know in General that their Souls have equal force; their Wiſdom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Inferior, nor their Thoughts confin'd to narrower Limits than what comprehends the Soul of Man. Through this thin Webb, that would
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42968:80"/>in vain obſcure their Luſtre, many have broken, contemning degenerate plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures inglorious Sloath and Eaſe, and chooſing the better part, by which they let men ſee they were no whit Inferior to them, in what might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them accompliſh'd, and make them Bloſſom in the duſt, as in ſundry rare Examples appears, in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of the Book. Nor are all Women-kind leſs capable in ſome degree or other, to improve thoſe Golden opportunities that God has put into their hands.</p>
                  <p>Women as I have often ſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of Virtue, the Limit her Creator ſet, is the moſt admirable Creature in the Univerſe, a Creature ſo charming, that we read the Sons of God beholding the Daughters of Men, that they were fair, did not diſdaign to Eſpouſe them, from which happy Union mighty <hi>Hero's</hi> ſprung.</p>
                  <p>Thus much may ſuffice to prove that there is an equality of the Soul, and that it is Independent but on God, who is it's Author and Inſtructor; as for the Body it is evidently no leſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42968:81"/>as ſome will object, it is made to ſuffer in caſe of Generation, but that which they account a weakneſs, whereby woman is render'd inferior to man, proves her Glory, and ought to be the chiefeſt Boaſt, not only Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the God of Nature, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders therein, as an immediate ſignal of Almighty Favour; his everlaſting Covenant appears in this as Lively as when firſt he Bleſt our Parents in their happy <hi>Eden;</hi> when affable and mild, with Aſpect Calme, he Shone upon them in his Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and became their great Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, e're his Brows were wrinkled with their diſobedience; e're his Adored Face chang'd into Terror, too ſevere for Mortals to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Beautious Ladies,</hi> who in <hi>Virtue</hi> ſtrive</l>
                     <l>To ſhame bold <hi>Vice,</hi> and keep the <hi>World</hi> alive.</l>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:42968:81"/>
                     <l>I have my <hi>Reaſon's</hi> to a Period brought,</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Writ</hi> no more than dwelt within my <hi>Thought;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reaſons</hi> that may induce you to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Makers</hi> gift, to gain your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> love;</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Gallantry,</hi> what <hi>Gory,</hi> what <hi>Renown</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beneath the <hi>Skies,</hi> is worth a <hi>Starey-Crown?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Conſider that, Conſider yet again,</l>
                     <l>If any Creatures Love you fain wou'd win,</l>
                     <l>Virtu'l Inamour the bright <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bim.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:42968:82"/>
                  <head>Reaſons drawn from the Immortality and wonderful Operation of the Soul, more fully proving the Excellency of Woman-kind.</head>
                  <p>THe foregoing Conſiderations duly weighed and impartially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, may give the Unbias'd part of Man-kind a juſt reaſon to believe that that deſerving Sex may juſtly claim an Equality in Wit, and be as capable of attaining the profoundeſt Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences as Man; for it is not the Body, but the Rational Soul, Noble in its ſelf, as being a ſpark of the Divine Eſſence that center knowledge: For as all Creatures Inferiour to Man-kind have their Life in their Blood, as it is Teſtified in the ſeventeenth of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus;</hi> ſo the Life of Man, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of Woman conſiſteth in the Soul, which although by reaſon of the groſs Humidity of the Body is ſubject to ſundry paſſions, ſome more Nobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> than others, yet it being Immorta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cannot in its ſelf ſuffer change, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:42968:82"/>a part of the Divine Mind, and Blaſt of Almighty Breath, that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes us from other Creatures, and that every one Created in that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Idea,</hi> has a peculiar Soul ſeems to be apparent, in reſpect of the may differences in Judgments and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Manners and Affections, though it is no leſs certain that itſprings from one and the ſame Fountain of Life and Immortality.</p>
                  <p>It has occaſion'd ſundry diſputes amonſt the Learned of all Ages, in what part of the Body the Soul has its chief Reſidence; ſome affirm it has its Throne or Regal Seat in the Region of the Heart; others with the like confidence and more reaſon, conclude its Principal Seat is in the Brain, from whence proceed the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, faculties and actions, and by defu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it ſelf in operation, it enlivens every part with Heat and Force, with Spiritual Eſſence, with Supernatural Intelects and Underſtanding, and more particularly it communicates its force to the Heart by Arteries, Carotides and Sleepy Arteries, the ſtopage or
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42968:83"/>obſtruction of which cauſes deſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies of Mind, as I have declared in the foregoing Chapter, and this is indifferent to either Sex, why then ſhould not either Sex be equaly capable of great things? what ſhould be the reaſon as to the main, I have already given, and now come to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, which is the contentedneſs of the Noble Sex in complying with what Cuſtome and Tradition has render'd nature, and by their long continuance become as it were a Law; which Generous Woman expreſſing thereby a kind of a Virtue in her Obedience, is willing to ſubmit to, and render a Complyance with, as part of that duty ſhe ows to her Compeere, not through Fear, but Love, a Love fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſo Tranſcendent, that it near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly views with that of Angels, and is as Inviolate as the Ties of Nature, delighting themſelves within which Pale, many ſeek no higher happineſs on this ſide Heaven, practiſing on Earth to imitate that ſacred Love which comprehends Felicity beyond Expreſſion, and by contemplating
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42968:83"/>things above, wean themſelves from things below, not but that they are capable of any thing, that man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to, would they apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereto, and improve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therein? what Kingdom knows not this, if Envy or Ignorance caſt not a Miſt before their Eyes? Scepters have often deigned to Kiſs their hands; and in the Beautious Graſp ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd as aweful as when held by the rough Warriour. Many wholſome Laws own them their Original, and Juſtice has been impartially Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred: Mercy too has found a place, and the Oppreſs'd pluck'd out of the hands of the Oppreſſor: Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their protection has flouriſh'd in its Purity, and War been proſperous under their Heroick Conduct: Arts have flouriſh'd by their countenance and skill: Learning and Learned Men Indulg'd and Improv'd, great has been their Sagacity and countleſs their Labours, but more the Virtues that ſhine in them, no where elſe ſound brighter in their native Purity, even ſuch as have raiſe'd the admiration of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42968:84"/>the wiſeſt Sons of Men, and ought as a mark of goodneſs to have a valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eſtimation ſet upon them, that they may convince the folly of the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and ſhame the Envious, and ſo regulate the World, that men may not for want of better knowledge be impoſed on, to believe what is not, nor the wiſer ſort ſo far forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to diſhonour thoſe who are the honour of Man kind.</p>
                  <p>Greater things then theſe might be ſaid upon the Subject, but as to theſe Particulars, for breviti's ſake, what has been ſpoken may ſuffice, from which I ſhall proceed, to that which comes next to be conſider'd which is the happineſs Man Injoys in being made capable of poſſeſſing a Bleſſing exceeding all that he can fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon Earth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>So Soft ſo Loving, Charming and ſo Kind,</l>
                     <l>That all the Creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s to his uſe aſſign'd,</l>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:42968:84"/>
                     <l>Compriz'd in one, all that in them is rare,</l>
                     <l>Cannot by infinite degrees with this compare.</l>
                     <l>Search for the <hi>Unicorn</hi> of <hi>Indian</hi> Breed,</l>
                     <l>For the <hi>Camelian</hi> that on Air does feed,</l>
                     <l>For the gay <hi>Phenix</hi> in <hi>Arabian</hi> fields,</l>
                     <l>Or for the Gold and Gems that <hi>India</hi> yeilds,</l>
                     <l>With cold <hi>Imaus</hi> Top, <hi>Eagles</hi> Eyes then View,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Hibla</hi> cover'd with <hi>Milliferous</hi> Dew.</l>
                     <l>View <hi>Sharons</hi> Valleys all with Roſes ſpread,</l>
                     <l>An'th <hi>Cedar</hi> Crown, on <hi>Lebanon's</hi> Large head.</l>
                     <l>Behold the place where ſpotleſs <hi>Lillies</hi> grow,</l>
                     <l>In Native pride, or where the Rivers Flow,</l>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:42968:85"/>
                     <l>Rowling on Golden Sands their fluctant Waves,</l>
                     <l>Or where the Sea, which rich <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſpia</hi> Laves.</l>
                     <l>And leaves on the forſaken ſhore thoſe Gems</l>
                     <l>That Star-like glitter in Kings Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems.</l>
                     <l>View all the Spicie Grove whoſe Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grance greet</l>
                     <l>The Traveller, before his Eyes can ſee't.</l>
                     <l>View all the Gaudy Plumes which on the Wind,</l>
                     <l>With out-ſpread wings an eaſy paſſage find.</l>
                     <l>And all thoſe Animals Earth does contain,</l>
                     <l>To theſe, joyn thoſe that cut the ſwelling Main.</l>
                     <l>And ſtill add more let Floras Glory come,</l>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Ceres</hi> her Gold ſheaves with ſu eat brought home.</l>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:42968:85"/>
                     <l>And kind <hi>Pomona</hi> with her giving hand.</l>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Baccus</hi> who o're Men has large command.</l>
                     <l>Let theſe and what of this kind, though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s can frame,</l>
                     <l>In one unite, In one their worth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim;</l>
                     <l>Compar'd with Women, Scarce they'l find a name.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:42968:86"/>
                  <head>The Happineſs that accrues to Man in the poſſeſſion of ſo great a Bleſſing as a Virtuous Woman.</head>
                  <p>ABove all Earthly Bleſſings, for which Man ought to pay the moſt profound Adoration to the Tremendious Majeſty of Heaven; Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is deſervedly placed, as being a part of himſelf, and more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made for his ſollace and delight, a Bleſſing by which a multitude of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings redound to him, ſuch as cannot be receiv'd from any other Creature, becauſe the means and opportunity in them are wanting; nor did the wiſe Creator think ſit to order it otherwiſe, for as much as likeneſſes are moſtly deſired, and the Soul is ſo Eſſentially noble, that it deteſts Familiarity with any thing inferiour to its ſelf, looking down upon Creatures Irational, as things made for its Service, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to it as in indeed they are for Man was made to ſeve his Maker,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:42968:86"/>and all things elſe for the Service and Uſe of Man, wherefore nothing could be found complacient amongſt Iratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creatures; all the Beauty of the Univerſe look'd like a Clouded Star, till the bright Beauty of Female Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency appear'd, and like the Sun diſpeld thoſe Damps that heavineſs of Mind had rais'd; and ſo pleaſing at firſt was the Queen of Sublunar things, that <hi>Adam</hi> was wonderfully ſurpriz'd to behold any Mortal frame ſo fair; and ſome have fancy'd that e're he had better inform'd himſelf, he took her not to be of Mortal or Material ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and thus imagine him to have Accoaſted her.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Faireſt of Creatures, found the laſt but beſt,</l>
                     <l>How am I with a ſight ſo pleaſing bleſt!</l>
                     <l>If you are Mortal ſpeak: But O! I fear</l>
                     <l>No mortal frame ſo Beautious can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear!</l>
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:42968:87"/>
                     <l>So great a favour Heav'n will not give</l>
                     <l>To Mortal Man that muſt conſented live,</l>
                     <l>With what his Bounteous hand has given him,</l>
                     <l>And not deſire a dazling Seraphim;</l>
                     <l>Yet ſomething ſtrange does move my earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Soul,</l>
                     <l>Strange thoughts about my Feble Fabric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roul,</l>
                     <l>And to ſurpreſs them, 'tis in vain I ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>Without this Fair methinks I cannot live,</l>
                     <l>Loadſtone like my heart draws her, and ſhe</l>
                     <l>Like the Bleſt <hi>Nedle's</hi> moveing towards me.</l>
                     <l>O! Great Creator, now I well perceive</l>
                     <l>This is a Bleſſing thou intends to give,</l>
                     <l>A happy Bleſſing, which makes all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat,</l>
                     <l>A favour which muſt ſurely make me great,</l>
                     <l>Since I on Earth find ſuch a Charming Mate,</l>
                     <l>In whom methinks the Graces all appear,</l>
                     <l>And native Beauty ſhines as in it's ſphere,</l>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:42968:87"/>
                     <l>An aire ſo pleaſing from her Face doe ſty,</l>
                     <l>Such Roſes ſtaine her Cheeks with Crimſon dye,</l>
                     <l>Such Beams of light dart front her piercing Eye,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Lillies all her Beautious ſtructure ſpread,</l>
                     <l>And with their Whiteneſs mix the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Red,</l>
                     <l>So Charming is ſhe, that if not Enjoy'd,</l>
                     <l>All favours elſe are by that loſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But to come nearer to what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, Woman is certainly the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Earthly comfort Man can be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of poſſeſſing, as being rightly term'd the ſollace of his Life, and to Wave her, being part of his Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or an Inſtrument in the hand of the Almighty to ſave the World from deſolation; her virtues are for the moſt part admirable, and no leſs her judgment, and the other Intelectual faculties of her Soul. That, as I have prov'd being nothing Inferiour to that,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:42968:88"/>in which Man centers his largeſt Pride and Boaſt, imagining it (as it truly is) a Ray of Eſſence, a Effluence of his Maker. Woman from her Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with pretty Smiles delights the World, and Chears the hearts of her admiring Parents, and as ſhe grows, Virtue takes its place well pleas'd to dwell in ſuch a Fabrick, and brings as her Attendants, Modeſty, Sobriety and a wining Behaviour. No ſooner is Woman poſſeſs'd by Man in the happy State of Conubial Love, but ſhe furuiſhes him with a ſhower of Bleſſings, wrap'd in ſoft Delights and deck'd in Chaſteſt Charms; mild and plyant is her Temper, and her Cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards him decent, and comely her Behaviour, her Love is beyond Expreſſion, and her Tenderneſs ſuch, that ſhe values him on whom her heart is plac'd equal with all but her imortal happineſs, as for her Life ſhe counts it a Trifle, and had rather looſe it than her Honour; ſhe eſteems nothing on Earth too good for her Beloved, and inforces all her Charms to pleaſe and render him the happy Father of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42968:88"/>hopeful Children; ſhe is indeed his <hi>Internus Senſus,</hi> his ſecond ſelf, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhareing his Joys and Afflictions, and is not like a Swallow that ſings to the morning wake of his proſperity, and when the Winter of his Adverſity comes, takes her way upon the Winds to ſeek a warmer Sun; her Smiles are not to be bought with Silver, nor her Love to be purchac'd with Gold, but are freely and intirely plac'd upon her Beloved; great is her diligence to pleaſe him, and as great her care not to offend him; when he rejoyces, ſhe rejoyces; when he is griev'd, ſhe is ſad, ſimpathiſing with him in all things, and is the ſecret Cabinet in which he dare repoſe his Secrets, and find them there as ſafe as in his Soul; a Repoſitory ſhe is of his abſtruſeſt thoughts, and is ever tender of his honour, nothing ſhe thinks too good for him, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhe can do too much; in Health, ſhe takes care for his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and is wonderfully tractable in forwarding his Affairs, in Sickneſs; ſhe is more ſtudious for his Health then her Intreſt, and puts up her Prayers
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:42968:89"/>and Vows to Heaven for his recovery, Expreſſing in all her actions a careful Love and Tenderneſs, and in her Words a venerable Eſteem; ſo that without ſo great a virtue as Woman, Man muſt be miſerable and forlorn as to his temporal Condition; nor ought he to eſteem ſo great a Bleſſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy his largeſt Thoughts, nor render the Almighty leſs Tribute of Praiſe and Thanks-giving, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing that laſt beſt favour on him, which could only compleat his earthly Felicity.</p>
                  <p>In making Woman Nature has been Laviſh, and ſhew'd her curious Art in Forming a Creature ſoft and tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to allay the rough temper of Man by moderation and mildneſs, as the Fluid Aire prevents the Firey Region from Calcinating the Earth, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that outragious Element ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Man-kind. Great was the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Nature uſed (or rather the God of Nature) (not to refer ſo great a Work to ſecond cauſes) in framing the lovely ſtructure of the <hi>Softer Sex</hi> in every part, proporting what by
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42968:89"/>ſight or touch might yield delight, forgetting nothing that was admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it ſelf, or might be pleaſing to thoſe whoſe curions thoughts could ſcan the beſt Perfections; wonder not then why the Sex is ſo admir'd by all the ſages of the World, yet not ſo much as real Worth commands in true deſert, as has been often intimated in the foregoing Pages; why then ſhould Man decline ſo great a Bleſſing? why ſhould not he, who is ſo proud of being Rational, uſe his Rationalty to a right end, and by temporal Love founded on Virtue, ſtrive to raiſe his Soul to that which is Eternal endleſs, and not dated by degrees of time; a Love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable as Fate, ſounded on a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of Bleſſings, in converſation with Angels, Arch-Angels, Cherubims and Seraphims; Thrones, Dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Prince-doms Virtues and Powers, all the Starry Quire of Brightneſs and Batitude; and higher yet, for Love is God, and God is Love, by it the order of the Viſible World is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and things not viſible to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Eyes ſupported in their ſacred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42968:90"/>and concordence, 'tis that which makes all truly happy, and without it is no happineſs in this World, nor the World to come.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Then let us prize a Gift that is ſo fair,</l>
                     <l>So good, ſo juſt, that ſhe our love ſhould ſhare,</l>
                     <l>To a degree, too great to be expreſt,</l>
                     <l>Who of all Bleſſing Earth affords, is beſt,</l>
                     <l>Who only Crowns all Earthly Flappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</l>
                     <l>And does Man-kind beyond his wiſhes bleſs.</l>
                     <l>A greater Bleſſing Heav'n never gave</l>
                     <l>To Mortal Man, but him that Man did ſave.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:42968:90"/>
                  <head>The Reaſons why Mans Happineſs is not compleat on Earth without the Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creature Woman.</head>
                  <p>AS for the neceſſity of the Beautious Sex it is evident, not only for the ſake of Generation, but for that of Mutual Society; Man without them being as a Solitary Traveller, who Journeys through Wilderneſſes and Deſarts, where Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſeldome give his Eyes the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of beholding them; though ſome may object that the Converſation of Man with Man is materialy ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. I grant it is in general relating to indifferent affairs, but where the Soul claims a cloſer Union than ſuch Innocent diverſions can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that convers is of little moment. Woman was taken from Man, and therefore by a ſimpathy of Nature, and a ſecret contraction of the better part, ſhe conſiders in being cruel to her temporal Original; ſhe is cruel to her ſelf, and in that cruellty offends her Maker, unleſs a ſingular vow of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42968:91"/>Chaſtity interpoſes, wherein her aime is to be a ſpotleſs Virgin, that ſo ſhe may follow the Lamb that has taken away Original Sin, and given us leave and oppertunity to be Regenerate and Born again through Faith and Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on his meritorious Death and paſſion, but to come nearer to the concluſion,
<q>
                        <l>Eternal love ought to be our chief aim,</l>
                        <l>Life in our Saviours death we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly claim,</l>
                        <l>In his dear merits all our hopes muſt be,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Zone</hi> of our everlaſting life is he,</l>
                        <l>A bright <hi>Meridian</hi> of Eternity;</l>
                        <l>But how came this great Miſtery to paſs?</l>
                        <l>Eternal Widom the Prime Author was:</l>
                        <l>The thing is deep, and Mortal Minds are loſt,</l>
                        <l>Heav'n nows alone what this dear Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing coſt.</l>
                        <l>Conſider then, and let us ſtill adore</l>
                        <l>Omnipotence, which our weak nature bore,</l>
                        <l>Compaſſioning us; he lay'd aſide</l>
                        <l>Known Glory, &amp; diſpiſing ſhame, he dy'd</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>'raign o're Death, with Death he yet comply'd.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus far diſcours'd, I ſhall proceed to the Character of a Virtuous Woman in all her Capacities.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="characters">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:42968:91"/>
               <head>The GOLDEN CHARACTER Of a VIRTUOUS WOMAN In all her CAPACITIES.</head>
               <p>IN this caſe three things are more immediately to be conſider'd, <hi>viz</hi> The Virgin State, and thoſe of Marriage and Widdow-hood, and of theſe in their Order.</p>
               <div type="character">
                  <p>A Virtuous Virgin may be properly call'd the Treaſurey of Chaſtity and Innocence, delighting to live in that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:42968:92"/>Eſtate, that ſhe may have the better opertunity to do good, and render her ſelf an example of Piety; Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Humility are her conſtant Attendants, and Pride knows not her Dwelling: She delights not in much Diſcourſe, and flys from Vanity: the Sound of vain words renders her reſtleſs and uneaſie, till ſhe has found a retirement: Modeſty and a Comely Behaviour are the Ornaments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe deſires to be decked: Affable ſhe is, and of a ſweet Temper: her Words are few, and thoſe deliver'd with deliberation: amongſt Strangers ſhe rarely ſpeaks, unleſs ſhe be ask'd any Queſtion, or otherwiſe Buſineſs of Importance requires it: ſhe chooſeth not a ſingle Life for it ſelf, but in Refference to her better ſerving God: ſhe improves her ſingle life therewith to ſerve God more conſtantly: ſhe counts her ſelf better loſt in modeſt Silence then found in bold Diſcourſe: at the Repetition of any wanton Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhe Bluſhes and turns away: for the future ſhuning thoſe that give themſelves up to ſuch Vanity, yet
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42968:92"/>when at any time ſhe mentions Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age it is done with ſeemly Reverence and regard to that Holy State: her Obedience to her Parents is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Reſpects to her Superiours equals and inferiours no leſs; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed lives a Saint-like life upon Earth, void of offence towards God and Man; and as ſhe lives with leſs Care, ſo ſhe dies with more Chearfulneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="character">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:42968:93"/>
                  <head>THE CHARACTER Of a VIRTUOUS WIFE.</head>
                  <p>NOT without Reaſon do's the Holy Scriptures Stile a good Woman or Wife, the Crown of her Husband, for ſo ſhe proves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt Felicity a Man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable off, being properly call'd his ſecon Self the Partner of his Joy and Grief, the ſafe Repoſitorie of his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, aand Sollace of his Life. A
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:42968:93"/>good Wife commandeth her Husband in equall Matter, by Conſtantly obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, ſhe never Croſſes him, in the height of his Anger, but patiently waits till it is abated, and then ſhe mildly argues the Matter with him, not ſo much to condemn him, as to acquit her ſelf. Her Husbands Secrets ſhe ſeals up in her Breaſt. In her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands abſcence, ſhe Officiates his place, in regarding and takeing care of his Affaires, but when he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſhe Intermedles in his concerns no further than ſhe is required, ſhe keeps at home conſtantly, unleſs ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſions require the contrary, and then ſhe acquaints her Husband therewith, and has his leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe ſets forward, her Habit and Attire, is rather Neat than Coſtly, her Carriage is Modeſt, and her Words deliver'd with a mixture of Diſcretion and Gravetie: In her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Afflictions, ſhe ever bears a part, and uſes her Endeavours to Conſolate him: Her Children though many in Number, are none in Noiſe, her Nod or Look, being a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:42968:94"/>ſufficient Helm to Steer them as ſhe pleaſes. The heavieſt Work of her Servants, is made Light, by her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and ſeſonable Enjoyning it. Wherefore her Service, is counted a Preferment, and her Teaching, better then Wages, and thus' ſhe is happy in her ſelf, and renders others the like Felicity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="character">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:42968:94"/>
                  <head>THE CHARACTER Of a VIRTUOUS VVIDDOVV.</head>
                  <p>AVirtuous Widdow has been the Eſteem of all Ages, and found the Miracle of Piety, for the near approach of Death, even to taking from them the Center of their Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections, makes paſt doubt a deeper impreſſion than can be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and fills their Penſive Breaſts with ſerious Thoughts, which turn to Meditations; and from thence as from a Fountain flows a ſtream of Prayers and Pious Ejaculations, which ſeldome are ſilent till the higheſt has regarded them. As for the Virtuous Widdow, though her Grief is real, yet it is moderate:
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:42968:95"/>ſhe doth not only live Sole and Single, but Chaſt and Honeſt, Though ſhe go abroad ſome times, about her bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſs, ſhe never makes it her buſineſs to go abroad, ſhe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Loves the Memory of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Husband, and will hear no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpoke off him, ſhe Cheriſhes her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and Fancies in them their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Idea:</hi> ſhe puts her Eſpecial Confidence in God, <hi>the Father to the Fatherleſs, and Husband to Widdows:</hi> ſhe is Carefull and Tender of her Reputation, yet not more Carefull of her own Credit, then of Gods Glory: ſhe is Pittyfull and Bounty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to People in Diſtreſs: ſhe walks Humbly before God in all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Duties: ſhe affects not the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Fooliſh Faſhions: ſhe roads con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Lectures to herſolf of her own Mortality, and in this State ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues all the Days of her apointed Time, 'Till her Change come.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:95"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS,</hi> newly Printed for <hi>John Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> againſt the Church in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">[1] A <hi>Diſcourſe of Divine Providence.</hi> 1. <hi>In General:</hi> That there is a Providence exerciſed by God in the World. 2. <hi>In Particular:</hi> How all Gods Providences in the World, are in order to the good of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. By the late Learned Divine <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Charnock, B. D.</hi> ſometimes <hi>Fellow</hi> of <hi>New-Colledg</hi> in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 3<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p n="2">[2] A Pleaſant and Compendious <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the firſt <hi>Inventers</hi> and <hi>Inſtituters</hi> of the moſt Famous <hi>Arts, Miſteries, Laws, Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> in the whole <hi>World.</hi> Together, with many other Rarities and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable things rarely known, and never before made publick. To which are Added, ſeveral Curious Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, peculierly attributed to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men. The whole Work Alphabetically Digeſted, and very helpful to the Readers of Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 1<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:96"/>
            <p n="3">[3] A <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> upon the <hi>Phariſee</hi> and the <hi>Publicane.</hi> Wherein ſeveral great and weighty things are handled: As the Nature of Prayer, and of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Law, with how far it obliges Chriſtians, and wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts: Wherein is alſo ſhewed the equally deplorable condition of the <hi>Phariſee,</hi> or Hypocritical &amp; Self-righteous Man, and of the <hi>Publicane,</hi> or Sinner that lives in Sin, and in open violation of the Divine Laws: Together with the Way and Method of God's Free-Grace in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Penetent Sinners; proving that he juſtifies them by imputing Chriſts Righteouſneſs to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 1<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p n="4">[4] <hi>SIghs from Hell,</hi> Or, The <hi>Groans of a Damned Soul.</hi> Diſcovering, from the 16th of <hi>Luke,</hi> the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate of the Damned. And may fitly ſerve, as a Warning-Word to Sinners, both Old and Young, by Faith in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to avoid the ſame place of Torment. With a Diſcovery of the Uſefulneſs of the Scriptures, as our ſafe Conduct for avoiding the Torments of Hell. Both by <hi>John Bunyon,</hi> Author of the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 1<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:96"/>
            <p n="5">[5] <hi>THe Saints Comfort,</hi> in all, but more eſpecially in Evil <hi>Times.</hi> Drawn from Twelve ſeveral Texts of Scripture; which are brieſly explained in this ſmall Piece. By <hi>T. G. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 1<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p n="6">[6] <hi>THE True Fortune-Teller:</hi> Or, <hi>Guide to Knowledge.</hi> Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the whole Art of <hi>Chyromancy, Phyſiognomy, Metopoſcopy,</hi> and <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</hi> Containing, 1. A Diſcription of the Planets, their power and influence over the Bodies of Men, Women, and Children. 2. Of the ſeveral Lines, Mounts, Marks, Angles, and ſacred Characters in the Hand and Wriſt; and by what Planets they are Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to good or bad Fortune. 3. Of <hi>Phyſiognomy.</hi> 4. Obſervations on the Eyes, Eye-brows, Noſe, Ears, Chin, Neck, Hair, Beard, and Face. 5. Metopoſcopy, or the ſignification of the Lines in the Face. 6. Of Moles and their ſignifications. 7. Of Dreams and their Interpretations. 8. Of Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their Calculation. 9. Of the Rod by which hidden Treaſure is found. 10. Of Marriages, and at what time any Perſon ſhall be Married. 11. Rules
<pb facs="tcp:42968:97"/>to know the danger of Death. 12. Of good and bad Days. 13. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Reſolving doubtful Queſtions, as to Friends, Marriages, places of Abode, Health, Proſperity or Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Love or Buſineſs. 14. Of <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> his Wheel of Fortune. 15. Of the good and bad days in each Month rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Health. To which are added, <hi>Ariſtoteles</hi> Obſervations of the Heavens, their motion. Of Firy Metors, Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Lightning, Eclipſes, Commets, Earth-quakes, and Whirl-winds. Illuſtrated with ſeveral proper Figures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 1<abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p n="7">[7] A Directory for Midwives: or a guide for Women, in their Conception. Bearing and Suckling their Children. The firſt part contains, 1. The Anatomy of the veſſels of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2. The Formation of the Child in the Womb. 3. What hinders concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and its remedies. 4. what furthers conception. 5. A guide for women in conception. 6. Of miſcarriage in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. 7. A guide for women in their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. 8. A guide for women in their Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in. 9. Of Nurſing children. by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Culpepper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound</hi> 3 <abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42968:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
